<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The moderate Independent proposing a word in season to the gathered churches, the Episcopal and Presbyterian parties tending to their humiliation for what is past, to be reconciled to each other for the time to come, and joyntly to acquiesse in the determinations of this present Parliament, as to the government of church &amp; state / by Salem Philalathes ...</title>
            <author>Philalathes, Salem.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 110 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16471</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13033151</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13033151</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51062)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 745:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The moderate Independent proposing a word in season to the gathered churches, the Episcopal and Presbyterian parties tending to their humiliation for what is past, to be reconciled to each other for the time to come, and joyntly to acquiesse in the determinations of this present Parliament, as to the government of church &amp; state / by Salem Philalathes ...</title>
                  <author>Philalathes, Salem.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96787:1"/>
            <p>THE Moderate Independent, PROPOSING A Word in Seaſon TO THE GATHERED CHURCHES, The EPISCOPAL AND PRESBYTERIAN Parties: Tending to Their Humiliation for what is paſt; To be Reconciled to each other for the time to come: AND Joyntly to Acquieſſe in the Determinations of this Preſent PARLIAMENT, as to the Government of CHURCH &amp; STATE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>SALEM PHILALATHES</hi> A Church-Member.</p>
            <q>Let your Moderation be known unto all men,</q>
            <bibl>Phil. 4. 5.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96787:2"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap> was retiring from his Court) was preſented by him with a <hi>little Book,</hi> in the <hi>Beginning, Middle</hi> and <hi>End</hi> thereof was only written <hi>Moderation, Moderation, Moderation:</hi> By which he inſinuated that <hi>Moderation</hi> was the only way to make both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> happy in each other. And if ſo, to reſtore both <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People</hi> to it, that have loſt it by running into <hi>Extreams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though therefore our <hi>Breaches</hi> ſeem to be like the Breaches of the Sea, which can hardly be reſiſted, or made up <hi>again,</hi> and the fierce <hi>Contentions,</hi> devouring Diviſions and <hi>Differences</hi> that have been <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween</hi> all <hi>Parties,</hi> ſeem to be like the <hi>Contentions</hi> amongſt <hi>Brethren,</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> tels us <hi>are like the Bars of a Caſtle,</hi> which naturally are baracadoed to <hi>reconciliation</hi> and accomodation with each other again: <hi>A Brother offended being harder to be won than a ſtrong City, Prov.</hi> 18. 19. Yet if that our own iniquities and the Jeſuits ſubtilties hinder not, there is a way to unite us all together, and to pluck up the <hi>Cauſes</hi> of all our Diſſentions by the <hi>Roots,</hi> and that is by <hi>Moderation, Moderation, Moderation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is <hi>Moderation,</hi> a Chriſtian <hi>Condeſcention</hi> to, and <hi>Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> with each other, that I <hi>profeſs</hi> that I <hi>propound</hi> as the end of my <hi>impartial</hi> and <hi>plain dealing</hi> with you all.</p>
            <p>And that I may remove that which is the great <hi>Impediment</hi> and <hi>Hinderance</hi> thereof amongſt all parties, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>high opinion</hi> and <hi>conceit</hi> they have of themſelves; all their waies being as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>right in their own eyes, that all others have wronged them,</hi> and they have been <hi>injurious to none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though I may ſeem (peradventure to ſome of you) to ſpeak as one more likely to widen, than to heal the Breaches now amongſt us, by ſome ſmart paſſages and expreſſions.</p>
            <p>Yet I intreat you all to conſider, that what I have written that may give any of you occaſion ſo to <hi>think,</hi> is only out of my <hi>unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned deſire</hi> to <hi>remove</hi> that great <hi>Impediment</hi> aforeſaid to <hi>Moderation,</hi> out of the <hi>way</hi> from all <hi>Parties.</hi> And that we may not be ſlightly <hi>healed,</hi> it is, that I ſo often ſeem to <hi>ſearch</hi> you to the <hi>quick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not therefore I beſeech you, any thing that hath dropt from my Pen, be taken by the wrong Handle, and be ſo far per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, as to heighten your <hi>paſſions</hi> and <hi>prejudices</hi> againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but as all <hi>Parties</hi> have joyned together by their <hi>ſins</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the <hi>Divine Majeſty,</hi> thus wofully to <hi>wound</hi> us, and almoſt <hi>tear</hi> us all to <hi>pieces;</hi> ſo let us call upon one another, in the words
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96787:2"/>
of the Prophet, <hi>Come and let us return unto the Lord; for he hath ſmitten us, and he will heal us, he hath torn us, and he will bind us up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, let me in the firſt place make my addreſs to you of the <hi>Epiſcopal Party,</hi> whether of the <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laytie,</hi> as you diſtinguiſh.</p>
            <p>Far be it from me to ſuggeſt any thing that might irritate and <hi>provoke</hi> you; except to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>good works.</hi> Yet give me leave to tell you that the great encouragement that <hi>generally</hi> hath been given to <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> and the <hi>Scorn, Oppoſition</hi> and <hi>Perſecution</hi> of <hi>Godly men,</hi> in all ages, from the time of <hi>Reformation,</hi> till God brought this <hi>Judgment</hi> upon us; I fear hath much provoked the <hi>Holy One of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That it hath been a ſinne of a <hi>long ſtanding</hi> amongſt you, whereof you are highly guilty. <note n="*" place="margin">And Dr. <hi>Jack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of C. C. he alſo confirms what I affirm, in many places of his works; eſpecially in <hi>Fol.</hi> 3660. In a Sermon of his Preached to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> ſpeaking to ſuch perſons whom he ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers of the Church,</hi> and his <hi>Respective Brethren,</hi> ſaith he, ſpeaking of the ſtupidity of this Nation under Gods Hand, who had lately viſited it with the Plague, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the City of <hi>Oxford</hi> in particular, ſaith he, ſhould a <hi>Stage-Player</hi> or other Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of <hi>Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> turn or have entred theſe ſuburbs within two moneths after our 4th. or 5th. viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion paſt, <hi>more</hi> of better rank amongſt us, would have been <hi>more</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of being cenſured as <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> for ſpeaking <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> (though in this place) then would have <hi>bluſhed</hi> to have been ſpectators of their moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable ſporting.</note> I ſhall preſent you with <hi>a complaint</hi> of that Pious and Learned <hi>Biſhop Downam,</hi> in his Sermon preached at Spittle, above forty years ago, called <hi>Abrahams Trial,</hi> p. 72. <hi>Even in theſe times,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Godly live amongſt ſuch a generation of men, that if a man do but labour to keep a good Conſcience in any meaſure, though he meddle not with matters of State, or Diſcipline, or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; As for example, If a Miniſter diligently preach, or in preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeek to profit rather then pleaſe; remembring that ſaying of the Apoſtle, If I ſeek to pleaſe men, I am not the Servant of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1. 10. <hi>Or if a private Chriſtian make Conſcience of ſwearing, ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the Sabbath, frequenting Sermons, or abſtaining from the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the times, he ſhall ſtraightway be condemned for a Puritan, and conſequently find leſs favour than either a Carnal Goſpeller or a cloſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemeth in thoſe daies perſons of meek and quiet Spirits, though conformable to the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> met with the <hi>perſecution</hi> of the Tongue, under the odious and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful name of <hi>Puritan;</hi> and found leſs favour than <hi>Prophane ones</hi> or <hi>Papiſts.</hi> How you proceeded to higher degrees, not only of the Tongue, but Hand, to the <hi>Silencing, Suſpending,</hi> and <hi>impriſoning</hi> of many <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Conformable Miniſters,</hi> that would not <hi>publiſh</hi> that <hi>woful Book</hi> for the <hi>Prophanation</hi> of the <hi>Lords Daies;</hi> forcing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Godly Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to leave their <hi>Native Country,</hi> and flee into <hi>New-England, Holland,</hi> and other <hi>Places.</hi> The <hi>firſt Remonſtrance</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> begun in <hi>Nov.</hi> 1640. doth at large <hi>demonſtrate;</hi> together with thoſe many <hi>Speeches</hi> ſpoken by Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96787:3"/>
Deering,</hi> my Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> that were no <hi>Puritans,</hi> nor yet for the <hi>total abolition</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Speeches and Paſſages of Parliament, p. 98. Printed for <hi>William Cooke</hi> at <hi>Furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls</hi> Inne Gate in <hi>Holbourne,</hi> 1641.</note> Saith Sir. <hi>Edward Deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, The Pride, the Avarice, the Ambition, the Oppreſſion of our ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Clergy, is Epidemical, it hath infected them all: There is not any, or ſcarce any of them, which is not practical in their own great cauſe in hand, which they impiouſly do miſcall the</hi> Piety of the times, <hi>but in truth ſo wrong a</hi> Piety; <hi>that I am told to ſay,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>In Facinus juraſſeputes—</hi> So he.</q>
            <p>And ſaith my Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> P. 65. of the ſame Collections, <hi>There is no man within theſe walls more ſenſible of the heavy grievance of Church-Government than my ſelf, nor whoſe affections are more keen to the clipping of thoſe wings of the Prelates, whereby they have mounted to ſuch Inſolency; nor whoſe zeal is more ardent to the ſearing of them, that they may never ſpring again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſuppoſe you are ſo eaten up with the ſenſe of your own <hi>ſufferings,</hi> that you have forgotten the <hi>occaſion</hi> you gave to many of <hi>Gods people</hi> to cry out to God againſt you their <hi>hard Taskmaſters.</hi> Let my Lord <hi>Digby</hi> be your <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> p. 70. <hi>Me thinks the vengeance of the Prelates hath been ſo laid, as if it were meant, no Generation, no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, no complexion of mankind ſhould eſcape it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was there a man of a nice and tender Conſcience, him they afflicted with ſcandal in</hi> adiaphoris, <hi>impoſing on him thoſe things as neceſſary, which he thinks unlawful, and they themſelves know to be but indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was there a man that made the Eſtabliſhment by Law, the meaſure of his Religion, him have they netled with innovations, with freſh introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was there a man of a meek and humble Spirit, him have they tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled to dirt in their pride.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was there a man that durſt mutter againſt their Inſolencies, he may enquire for his Lugs, they have been within the Biſhops Viſitation. As if they would not only derive their Brandiſhment of the Spiritual Sword from Saint Peter, but of the material one too, and the right to cut off Ears.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now as it was thus with the <hi>Governours</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> who u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually did <hi>exerciſe</hi> their <hi>Severity</hi> in all their <hi>Viſitations,</hi> upon ſuch as could not upon <hi>Conſcientious</hi> Grounds conform to their ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> &amp;c. as my Lord <hi>Digby witneſſeth</hi> againſt them. So the ſubordinate <hi>Clergy</hi> for the <hi>moſt part,</hi> were of <hi>ambitious</hi> and <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96787:3"/>
ſpirits, and of ſuch vicious lives and <hi>converſations,</hi> that like the <hi>prophane</hi> Sons of <hi>Eli,</hi> they made many to <hi>adhor the Offerings of the Lord.</hi> And in ſtead of preſſing upon the people the <hi>neceſſity</hi> of <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generation</hi> and <hi>holineſs,</hi> without which no <hi>enterance</hi> into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Heaven;</hi> to that <hi>holy Singularity</hi> and <hi>preciſeneſs</hi> which the Word of God requires; the moſt of their <hi>zeal</hi> vented it <hi>ſelf,</hi> in <hi>cloſe Sarcaſmes</hi> at <hi>Purity</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> though it was their <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in their <hi>Desks,</hi> that the reſt of our <hi>lives</hi> hereafter might be <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all which do but call to mind that <hi>general Prophaneneſs</hi> that had overrun the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> in <hi>Court, City</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> and you will find that you have no great cauſe to look upon <hi>your ſelves</hi> as <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Martyrs</hi> in what you have <hi>ſuffered</hi> from <hi>God</hi> and <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Surely</hi> that <hi>Flood of Prophaneneſs</hi> that now again <hi>begins</hi> to ariſe, and that extream <hi>violent Spirit</hi> that appeareth ſtill among many of you, doth <hi>evidence,</hi> that though God hath <hi>humbled</hi> you and brought you <hi>low,</hi> that yet you have not humbled your ſelves under the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Hand of God,</hi> nor have yet <hi>repented</hi> to give him <hi>Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be wiſe therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed ye Judges and Rulers of</hi> the Earth; <hi>Kiſs</hi> the Son, leſt his <hi>anger</hi> which he hath made to <hi>ſmoak</hi> againſt you, be further incenſed, to your <hi>Ruine.</hi> And you of the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> If you have no <hi>zeal</hi> for the <hi>Honour</hi> of your <hi>Maſter Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> you pretend to be; or <hi>pitty</hi> to the <hi>precious Souls</hi> of men; yet if there be in you any <hi>real reſpect</hi> to the reſtoring of your <hi>Soveraign</hi> to the <hi>Government</hi> of the Land, and his proſperous and peaceable Government, preach down that horrid prophaneſs that ſtill appears in the moſt of thoſe that eſpouſe his <note n="*" place="margin">I mean the prophane Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natick, who in this juncture of time that they have but a litle hope of peace, fall to ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, drinking, and other waies of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, that we may juſtly fear, may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord to repent of the Good he hath begun a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us. Dr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> hath drawn the Character of our preſent condition in the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and other places to the life, <hi>Fol.</hi> 3660. Comparing us to the City of <hi>Trireres,</hi> one of the moſt flouriſhing Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties amongſt the <hi>Gilles,</hi> who were ſo intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratly ſet upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their wonted delights, that after the City had been ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 4 times, and did not retain ſo much as the likeneſs of w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it had been, yet <hi>they were still the ſame.</hi> No ſooner was this ſtorm of Blood &amp; War broken up, and the Beams of Peace reſtored again, but they erected their Stages even in the freſh ſent of deadly Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours from their murdered Citizens, buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Aſhes.</note> 
               <hi>Intereſt:</hi> preſs them to follow as much after <hi>Holineſs</hi> as they do <hi>Peace;</hi> without <hi>which they ſhall never ſee God.</hi> Exhort them to <hi>Repentance</hi> for their <hi>preſent</hi> incorrigibleneſs under Gods Hand: Urge them to a <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Moderation.</hi> And be ye <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary</hi> to them in all theſe things. And do not ſtill <hi>diſcover</hi> your <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>obſtinacy</hi> by a <hi>violent purſuit</hi> of a <hi>reſtoration</hi> and <hi>return</hi> to your former <hi>worldly Pomp</hi> and <hi>Greatneſs,</hi> your <hi>Domineering Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> as to <hi>Government,</hi> your former <hi>ſplendid, ſuperſtitious</hi> and <hi>cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious</hi> Service of <hi>God.</hi> Why ſhould either <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laitie</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that what pleaſeth their own <hi>carnal Fancies</hi> in <hi>Gods Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> is <hi>pleaſing</hi> to him who is a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and will be <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt</hi> in <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi> Our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> is of another <hi>mind,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:96787:4"/>
and tels us, <hi>Luke 16. 15. That which is highly eſteemed amongſt men, is abomination in the ſight of God.</hi> And ſo alſo is one of your <hi>Judgment, Learned</hi> Mr. <hi>John Hales,</hi> in his Works ſet forth by Mr. <hi>John Pierſon,</hi> Page, 172. Saith he, <hi>Quid juvat hoc noſtres Templis admittere mores? Why meaſure we God by our ſelves, and becauſe we are led with gay ſhews and goodly things, think it is ſo with God. Seneca</hi> reports, <hi>that a</hi> Pantomimus, <hi>a Puppet-Player and Dancer in</hi> Rome, <hi>becauſe that he pleaſed the people well, was wont to go up every day into the Capitol, and practiſed his Art, and danced before</hi> Jupiter, <hi>and thought he did the god a great Pleaſure.</hi> Beloved, <hi>In many things we are like this Puppet Player, and do much meaſure God by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by the world:</hi> Becauſe that your <hi>gay</hi> and <hi>guilded Churches,</hi> your <hi>golden Copes</hi> and <hi>Organs,</hi> your ſquare Caps, Rochets, Lawn Sleeves, and Sirplices, your Cringing and Bowing, your Dopping and Ducking to the High Altar, your Dancing up and down from place to place, to read the firſt and ſecond Service, with many <hi>frivolous, ſuperfluous</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious Ceremonies,</hi> pleaſed your <hi>ſelves</hi> and the <hi>ignorant People,</hi> therefore you thought <hi>God</hi> was pleaſed therewith alſo. But if you conſult with Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> he tels you, <hi>P. 170. That to add to the Church outward Statelineſs and Pomp, is nothing elſe but to make a Centaure; marry and joyn the Kingdom of Chriſt with the Kingdom of the world: a thing which I do the rather note</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>becauſe the long continuance of ſome Ceremonies in the Church, having occaſioned many, eſpecially of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>to think that there is no Religion, no Service, without theſe Ceremonies,</hi> &amp;c. How far <hi>you</hi> were gone towards <hi>Rome</hi> in this <hi>reſpect,</hi> your <hi>ſilencing</hi> many <hi>Godly, Orthodox</hi> and Able Preachers, for not <hi>conforming</hi> to your <hi>Superſtitious Ceremonies,</hi> doth witneſs againſt you: And that you remain ſtill of the ſame mind, <hi>that there is no Religion, nor Service without theſe Ceremonies,</hi> your <hi>violent Deſires</hi> and high Hopes to ſee them again impoſed, doth abundantly <hi>declare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me therefore perſwade you to more <hi>Moderation.</hi> And though you have as our aforeſaid <hi>Author</hi> ſaith, <hi>fallen too much upon that</hi> Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 170.</note> 
               <hi>Conceit, that in his Travels, ſeeing the Beams and Poſts of Houſes ſquared and carved asked, if the Trees grew ſo in thoſe Countries? ſo ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been long acquainted with a Form of Worſhip, ſquared and carved, trickt and ſet out with ſhew, and Ceremony; have been apt to think that Trees grow ſo; that there is no natural ſhape and Face of Gods Worſhip.</hi> Yet he will tell you, that <hi>abinitio non fuit ſic,</hi> and this he doth <hi>learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96787:4"/>
and <hi>largely</hi> prove, <hi>p.</hi> 171. To which I refer you.</p>
            <p>Let therefore the woful miſeries and calamities which you have brought upon the Land, by ſo <hi>altering</hi> the Face of the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> ſince the <hi>Reformation</hi> thereof in Queen <hi>Elizabeths daies,</hi> through your ſo <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious Innovations;</hi> that you made it look ſo like the Painted <hi>Whore</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> that <hi>Sancta Clara</hi> hath publiſhed, <hi>That the Face of our Church began to alter, the Language of our Religion to change; and ſetting Puritans aſide, our Articles and their Religion would ſoon be agreed.</hi> Let alſo your <hi>violent</hi> urging <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> to theſe <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> which you made the <hi>Devils Sieves</hi> to winnow <hi>Pious men</hi> of <hi>Tender Conſciences,</hi> out of their <hi>Miniſterial</hi> Employments: I ſay, let theſe with your many other <hi>Provocations</hi> of the <hi>Divine Majeſty, meeken</hi> and <hi>moderate</hi> your Spirits, reſtrain your eager purſuit of <hi>Epiſcopacy in ſtatu corrupto,</hi> with its ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vanities; <hi>eſpecially</hi> conſidering how much <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> hath been <hi>expended</hi> in this <hi>Quarrel.</hi> My Lord <hi>Digby</hi> was of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind, before a Drop of Blood was ſpilt: Saith he, <hi>P. 74. Let us not deſtroy, but make Biſhops ſuch as they were in the Primitive times.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do their large Territories, their large Revenues offend? let them be retrencht: The good Biſhop of</hi> Hippo <hi>had but a narrow Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do their Courts and Subordinates offend? let them be brought to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern as in the Primitive times, by Aſſemblies of their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doth their intermedling in Secular Affairs offend? Exclude them from the capacity, it is no more than what reaſon and all antiquity hath interdicted them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That you may be glad of <hi>this</hi> when you can <hi>get it,</hi> and may <hi>meet</hi> with no further <hi>Obſtructions,</hi> I ſhall now direct my <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> to you of the Presbyterian Party.</p>
            <p>Who alſo have as great <hi>Cauſe</hi> to be <hi>humbled</hi> and <hi>repent,</hi> as the <hi>Party</hi> before ſpoken to, though not for the <hi>very ſame ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>great</hi> and <hi>cogent</hi> Argument by which <hi>God</hi> would <hi>reſtrain</hi> his people of old from <hi>oppreſſion</hi> of others, was this, the ſenſe of the <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions</hi> which they had lain under in the <hi>Land of Egypt:</hi> And one would think, this ſhould have <hi>reſtrained</hi> you, that groaned ſo much under the <hi>oppreſſion</hi> of your <hi>Conſciences</hi> and <hi>Eſtates.</hi> And yet no ſooner were you come out of <hi>great Tribulation</hi> your ſelves, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96787:5"/>
like that <hi>cruel Servant</hi> in the Goſpel, you fell to <hi>beating</hi> and <hi>wound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of your <hi>Fellowes</hi> in <hi>both.</hi> All that woful <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>ſeverity</hi> which you inflicted by <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> and <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> upon thoſe that could not <hi>joyn</hi> with you, in taking up of Arms, and in the <hi>Era<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication,</hi> in ſtead of the <hi>Reformation</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> while you were in <hi>Power,</hi> ſhould very much <hi>melt</hi> and <hi>molifie</hi> your hearts, and much <hi>incline</hi> them to accomodation and <hi>moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:</hi> Eſpecially conſidering with what little <hi>reſpect</hi> unto the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> of others ye violently <hi>impoſed</hi> upon them <hi>vowes</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> wherein you only were ſatisfied your <hi>ſelves:</hi> For <hi>refuſing</hi> whereof many <hi>Orthodox Miniſters</hi> loſt their <hi>Livings,</hi> that could not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe have been <hi>ejected</hi> as <hi>ſcandalous</hi> and <hi>inſufficient;</hi> but only for this particular <hi>Malignancy:</hi> Forgetting how much you cried out againſt the <hi>Biſhops new Oath,</hi> which they would have <hi>impoſed.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had you in this <hi>obſerved</hi> that Golden Rule of our Saviour, <hi>to do to others, as you would be done by:</hi> you would not to promote the Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of your <hi>own Party,</hi> have <hi>hewed</hi> out a <hi>Reformation</hi> with ſo much <hi>violence;</hi> and to impoſe a <hi>rigid Presbytery,</hi> have ſpared none of a <hi>different judgment</hi> from you, that ſtood in your way.</p>
            <p>I hope in all this time that <hi>God</hi> hath laid you aſide, ye who are what you <hi>profeſs</hi> your ſelves to be (whether <hi>Miniſters</hi> or <hi>people) ſuch as fear to offend the Divine Majeſty, and avoid all appearances of evil,</hi> have made ſome ſerious <hi>reflexions</hi> upon your ſelves, and have humbled your <hi>Soules</hi> before the <hi>Lord</hi> for your <hi>many miſcarriages,</hi> while you were in <hi>power,</hi> and for thoſe <hi>extreams</hi> into which you have <hi>run</hi> with the <hi>reſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure it was your <hi>Duty</hi> in the day of <hi>Adverſity</hi> to <hi>conſider.</hi> You ſhould have <hi>conſidered</hi> what might <hi>provoke</hi> the Lord againſt you, not only to <hi>diſappoint</hi> your hopes of ſetling your ſo much <hi>admired Church-Government,</hi> but alſo to bring the <hi>whole Miniſtry of theſe Nations</hi> as near to an utter <hi>extirpation,</hi> as you had <hi>brought</hi> thoſe that <hi>ordained you,</hi> and ſet you apart to the <hi>work of the Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>violence</hi> of many of your <hi>Spirits,</hi> which appeareth in this day-break of your hopes of deliverance from men of <hi>Antimonarchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> and <hi>Anti-miniſterial ſpirits,</hi> makes me think you have not truly and throughly been <hi>humbled</hi> for what is <hi>paſt.</hi> No marvel therefore that ſo many of you are ſo <hi>pertinacious</hi> in your way.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore let your <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Moderation</hi> be known unto all men, in giving over your <hi>violent</hi> purſuit of an <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96787:5"/>
and <hi>independent Presbytery,</hi> from the <hi>Angels</hi> of the <hi>Churches;</hi> and be of a condeſcending towards others, who may have as much <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> on their ſide, and may appear to be as <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>conſcientious</hi> as your <hi>ſelves.</hi> Do not think that there can be no <hi>purity</hi> of <hi>Ordinances,</hi> but where there is a <hi>Parity</hi> in their <hi>Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</hi> Neither any <hi>Reformation</hi> of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> without the <hi>extirpation</hi> of it <hi>root</hi> and <hi>branch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great <hi>Objection</hi> that lieth againſt this <hi>Motion</hi> is, that you lie under an <hi>Obligation</hi> by <hi>Covenant</hi> to extirpate the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore you cannot <hi>recede</hi> from it.</p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer, that an <hi>unlawful</hi> Oath <hi>bindeth</hi> not. Now whether that long League or <hi>Covenant</hi> (wherein were too many words to be without ſin) were <hi>lawful</hi> yea or no, I deſire you to <hi>compare</hi> it with thoſe <hi>Rules</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> of a <hi>lawful Oath</hi> or Vow laid down by the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> in their <hi>Humble Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> §. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Oath</hi> ſay they, <hi>muſt be impoſed by lawful Authority; whoſo takes it, is to avouch nothing but what he is fully perſwaded is the truth, what is good and juſt, and what he is able to perform, and bindeth not to ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I ſay, if you do but <hi>compare</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> with theſe <hi>Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications,</hi> you will I ſuppoſe be of my <hi>mind,</hi> that it calleth rather for your <hi>Humiliation,</hi> than your <hi>Ratification</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Peruſing ſome of your Proofs to theſe Particulars, I find <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 2, 3, 5, 6, 8. Before that <hi>Abrahams Servant</hi> would <hi>ſwear</hi> unto his <hi>Maſter,</hi> though the <hi>Oath</hi> was <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>ſhort,</hi> he puts in a <hi>Peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> v. 5. <hi>What if the woman will not come with me into the Land?</hi> Shall I then be <hi>diſcharged of my oath?</hi> v. 8. Surely if ye had <hi>fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Oath,</hi> ye might have <hi>propounded</hi> many doubts and <hi>ſcruples</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you had taken the <hi>Covenant</hi> your <hi>ſelves,</hi> or ſo <hi>harſhly</hi> impoſed it upon others, under ſuch <hi>ſevere penalties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. What if the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe <hi>Doctrine, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> (I underſtand not) will <hi>alter</hi> their way of <hi>Government,</hi> &amp;c. whether I <hi>will</hi> or <hi>no,</hi> Am I then <hi>diſcharged</hi> of <hi>my Oath?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. What if the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church by <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> &amp;c. being ſetled by the <hi>Law of England,</hi> cannot be <hi>remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> without a <hi>Law</hi> made by the <hi>Three</hi> Eſtates in <hi>Parliament,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96787:6"/>
of <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons:</hi> Is it not <hi>unlawful</hi> for me to <hi>ſwear</hi> the <hi>extirpation</hi> thereof? And does a new Oath impoſed without the <hi>Authority aforeſaid,</hi> bind me to <hi>obſerve it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. What if the <hi>Parliament</hi> whoſe <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges</hi> I ſwear <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely</hi> to <hi>preſerve,</hi> ſhall <hi>introduce Popery, Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> which is not to <hi>preſerve</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the true <hi>Religion,</hi> am I not then diſcharged of my Oath? ſeeing my <hi>Covenant</hi> ties me to defend his <hi>Majeſties Perſon</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> only with this <note n="*" place="margin">Which limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our loyalty to Kings, no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they preſerve the true Religion, neither the Word of God, the Oath of Allegiance, or the Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ye all took before this Covenant, doth not in the leaſt mention or allow: for therein ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the duty of your alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, to maintain and defend his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties royal Perſon and Eſtate.</note> limitation, in the <hi>preſervation</hi> and <hi>defence</hi> of the <hi>true Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many other things might have been <hi>ſuggeſted</hi> to this <hi>purpoſe.</hi> You ſhould do <hi>well</hi> to <hi>conſider</hi> whether you did not <hi>force</hi> many not only to <hi>ſwear,</hi> but to <hi>lie</hi> alſo, in affirming that they <hi>entred into this So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant, after other means of Supplication, Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtnance, Proteſtations and ſufferings,</hi> when they never had the leaſt hand in any of them, but meerly to prevent or mittigate their <hi>Sufferings</hi> under your <hi>hands,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo whether the greateſt number of thoſe that took the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> willingly, could be perſwaded of <hi>that which they did avouch as truth,</hi> that they <hi>entred into this Covenant, according to the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable practiſe of theſe Kingdoms in former times:</hi> Or whether it were not rather a <hi>manifeſt untruth.</hi> For except what was done in <hi>former times</hi> by the <hi>Kirk of Scotland,</hi> the <hi>Chronicles</hi> of <hi>England</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Hiſtory</hi> give no <hi>teſtimony</hi> to what you <hi>affirm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It appeareth therefore from theſe <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> and by the <hi>ſwallowing</hi> down of this <hi>Covenant</hi> ſo <hi>raſhly</hi> your ſelves, and <hi>impoſing</hi> it ſo <hi>harſhly</hi> upon others, that to one <hi>ſcruple of Conſcience,</hi> there was <hi>a pound of worldly wiſdom and carnal policy;</hi> and that the <hi>deſign</hi> of this <hi>Oath</hi> was to <hi>oblige</hi> men, more to a <hi>Party,</hi> than to <hi>Duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſpoken the more <hi>freely</hi> and <hi>largely</hi> of this buſineſs concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Covenant</hi> and its non-obliging <hi>power,</hi> becauſe that I have obſerved <hi>many Miniſters</hi> much bewail the backwardneſs of people to <hi>Covenant-Reformation,</hi> and the great guilt of <hi>Covenant-breaking</hi> they lie under: Yet never heard any to bewail the <hi>taking</hi> of it. Though by what hath been <hi>ſuggeſted,</hi> there is as much <hi>cauſe</hi> for the <hi>one</hi> as the <hi>other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore be <hi>perſwaded</hi> I beſeech you, in ſtead of a main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining what you have done, truly to <hi>repent</hi> for what is <hi>paſt;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially for your great <hi>ſeverity</hi> in impoſing it upon many others, who did as truly <hi>ſcruple</hi> that, as ſome of you did the <hi>Engagement:</hi> and I
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96787:6"/>
ſuppoſe many of you would have <hi>done</hi> the often attempted <hi>Oath of Abjuration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sirs, ye are now brought to the <hi>Touch-ſtone,</hi> whether ye be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuch as ye have publickly <hi>profeſſed</hi> your ſelves to be in your <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologetical Declaration,</hi> your <hi>ſerious Repreſentation</hi> and <hi>Vindication</hi> of your ſelves from the <hi>irregular actings</hi> of the <hi>Independent Party:</hi> That you were <hi>Friends</hi> to a <hi>Regulated Monarchy,</hi> to a <hi>Free Parliament,</hi> that you never intended the <hi>ſubverſion</hi> and change of the <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Lawes and <hi>Government</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> that it may appear that theſe were not the <hi>male-contented evaporations</hi> of a diſappointed <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> (as ſome are ſtill apt to judge, by the <hi>violence</hi> of many of your ſpirits, now you are again on the <hi>riſing ſide.</hi>)</p>
            <p>Let the ſenſe of thoſe miſeries and calamities which ye brought upon the <hi>State,</hi> by your <hi>violent</hi> attempts and endeavours <hi>totally</hi> to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and change the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> before the <hi>Treaty at the Iſle of Wight;</hi> the <hi>experience</hi> you have had of the great <hi>unpleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingneſs</hi> to all <hi>Parties,</hi> but your <hi>ſelves,</hi> of the way that you <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound.</hi> And as ever ye <hi>deſire</hi> to prevent the letting in of a <hi>ſweeping deſtruction</hi> at the <hi>gates</hi> of our <hi>Diviſions,</hi> which are never like to be <hi>compoſed,</hi> while you violently <hi>purſue</hi> that wherein the <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> hath ſo <hi>ſignally</hi> croſſed you, now <hi>prevail</hi> upon you to <hi>lay</hi> aſide your eager <hi>contention</hi> for an <hi>abſolute Presbytery:</hi> And <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> as becometh <hi>Chriſtians</hi> profeſſing Godlineſs, to be <hi>ſubject to Authority, acquieſce</hi> in the <hi>determinations</hi> of this <hi>great Council,</hi> the <hi>Parliament,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath ſo <hi>wonderfully</hi> brought <hi>together;</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the <hi>Government</hi> both of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to this purpoſe, as I have in particular addreſſed my ſelf to the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> ſo I alſo ſhall conclude with a word or two unto you of the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſtry.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is moſt <hi>evident,</hi> that your <hi>work</hi> as <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel is, to be <hi>inſtrumental</hi> in turning not only of the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>men</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> but alſo to <hi>turn</hi> and <hi>reconcile</hi> the <hi>hearts</hi> of men unto one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. It was <hi>propheſied</hi> of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who was a <hi>burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and a <hi>ſhining light,</hi> that he <hi>ſhould turn the hearts of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents to their Children, and of Children to their Parents,</hi> Mal. 4. Luke 1. 17. I deſire you to <hi>conſider,</hi> whether in ſtead of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>good work,</hi> ye had not a great hand formerly in <hi>turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>hearts of Children</hi> from their <hi>Parents,</hi> both <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil;</hi> when from your <hi>Pulpits,</hi> ye ſounded thoſe <hi>Allarmes</hi> to this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96787:7"/>
War, and ſo mightily provoked young people (who underſtood not the Quarrel) to leave both their <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Parents</hi> (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their <hi>conſent</hi>) and to adventure their lives in the high places of the field, for the <hi>Cauſe of Chriſt.</hi> I beſeech you therefore now be as <hi>forward</hi> in <hi>turning</hi> the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>Children</hi> to their <hi>Parents</hi> again: Take heed of raiſing and <hi>fomenting jealouſies</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> whereby to <hi>alienate</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> away the <hi>hearts</hi> of <hi>people</hi> from <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> to the <hi>Fathers</hi> of their <hi>Country.</hi> And as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> did this by the preaching of <hi>Repentance,</hi> by an <hi>impartial</hi> preſſing of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to the <hi>conſcionable</hi> performance of the <hi>duties</hi> of their particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>places</hi> and <hi>callings;</hi> ſo be ye perſwaded to do the like in this <hi>juncture</hi> of <hi>time. Preſs</hi> upon your <hi>Hearers,</hi> and charge upon their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> who are forward enough to make profeſſion of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> of the Firſt <hi>Table;</hi> to be <hi>conſcionable</hi> in the obſervance of the <hi>Duties</hi> of the <hi>Second,</hi> and eſpecially of that <hi>Fifth Command,</hi> to which the <hi>Promiſe</hi> of <hi>long life</hi> is <hi>made,</hi> and the <hi>violation</hi> whereof we have <hi>cauſe</hi> to fear, hath ſhortned the daies of <hi>many</hi> in this <hi>Nation,</hi> and ſent them to their <hi>Graves</hi> in <hi>Coffins</hi> of <hi>Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many there are I ſuppoſe, which have offended in this kind, through <hi>Ignorance,</hi> for want of <hi>Information</hi> from their <hi>Teachers.</hi> But that both <hi>good Miniſters</hi> and <hi>People</hi> are apt to <hi>forget</hi> themſelves, as to this <hi>Particular,</hi> though the <hi>Drums</hi> ſhould never have <hi>beaten</hi> it out of their <hi>Heads,</hi> is <hi>evident,</hi> by the <hi>memento</hi> that <hi>Paul</hi> giveth to <hi>Titus,</hi> Chap. 3. v. 5. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, and that they be obedient to Magiſtrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Certainly this Duty was never more in ſeaſon than now, to <hi>urge</hi> upon your <hi>Hearers,</hi> to be <hi>ſubject to Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers,</hi> and to be <hi>obedient</hi> to all the <hi>Lawful Commands</hi> of Magiſtrates, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>diſputing</hi> their <hi>expediency;</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> whereof they have no Call from <hi>God</hi> or <hi>man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as a further <hi>means</hi> to <hi>reconcile</hi> us unto one another, <hi>inſiſt</hi> much upon thoſe <hi>Duties</hi> which <hi>follow</hi> in the <hi>next verſe,</hi> and <hi>patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> exhort them thereunto, and <hi>diſſwade</hi> from thoſe contrary <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments</hi> to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>V. 2. <hi>That they ſpeak evil of no man, be no Brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs to all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doubtleſs were but this <hi>Goſpel</hi> Precept in this verſe, conſcionably <hi>practiſed,</hi> it would <hi>exceedingly</hi> tend to the <hi>healing</hi> of all our Breaches, and the making up of our <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Diviſions,</hi> by which we are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96787:7"/>
               <hi>conſumed.</hi> We have in order hereunto, <hi>bitten</hi> and <hi>devoured</hi> one another, not ſo much with our <hi>Teeth,</hi> as with our <hi>Tongues.</hi> To <hi>cure</hi> us, <hi>Put them in mind that they ſpeak evil of no man.</hi> There is none of us, but take too much <hi>liberty</hi> even to this <hi>day,</hi> to ſpeak <hi>contumeliouſly</hi> of thoſe which are not of their own <hi>Party,</hi> whereas there is nothing more <hi>clear</hi> than this, that we are under <hi>a Divine Charge</hi> and prohibition, to ſpeak <hi>evil of no man,</hi> of what <hi>Party</hi> ſoever. <hi>And that we be no Brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing all meekneſs to all men,</hi> is alſo another Goſpel Precept. To be <hi>affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> gentle and <hi>peaceable</hi> towards thoſe of our own <hi>judgments,</hi> and that are of our own <hi>Party,</hi> is no <hi>ſingular Act</hi> of <hi>Humanity.</hi> Our Saviour tels us, if we be <hi>friendly</hi> only to our <hi>Brethren,</hi> What <hi>ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> thing do ye, Do not even the <hi>Publicans</hi> the ſame? But to ſhew <hi>all meekneſs to all men,</hi> of what <hi>Party</hi> ſoever, you ſee is the <hi>bounden</hi> duty of thoſe to whom the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>appeared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Make uſe therefore of your <hi>Divine Oratory,</hi> to urge theſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Duties</hi> upon your <hi>Hearers,</hi> by all thoſe <hi>Arguments</hi> which are drawn up by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> to your <hi>Hands,</hi> in the 3, 4, &amp; 5. <hi>verſes</hi> of the ſame <hi>Chapter,</hi> and I doubt not, but by <hi>Gods Bleſſing,</hi> who is the <hi>God of Peace,</hi> he will once more <hi>bleſs</hi> his people with <hi>Peace,</hi> according to his <hi>Promiſe, The Lord who ſitteth upon the Flood, yea, the Lord who ſitteth King for ever, the Lord will give ſtrength unto his People, the Lord will bleſs his People with Peace,</hi> Pſal. 29. 10, 11.</p>
            <p>And that this <hi>Peace</hi> may not be <hi>obſtructed,</hi> but as <hi>vigorouſly</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued and <hi>followed</hi> after, as <hi>Holineſs,</hi> to both which we are <hi>equally</hi> engaged <hi>Jure Divino.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me now make my particular <hi>addreſs</hi> to ye of the <hi>Independent</hi>
               <note place="margin">To the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Party, or Gathered Churches.</note> 
               <hi>Party,</hi> and of the <hi>Gathered Churches;</hi> to whom though I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to ſay, which lie upon my <hi>heart,</hi> and I find my ſelf <hi>bound in Spirit</hi> to make mention of; yet in this <hi>time</hi> of <hi>trouble</hi> and <hi>day</hi> of <hi>Rebuke,</hi> which the <hi>Righteous Lord</hi> hath moſt juſtly brought upon us for our <hi>ſins.</hi> I find the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of our many <hi>Provocations,</hi> very much afflicting my heart with grief, and ſoul with ſorrow, under this <hi>aggravation;</hi> That though I have all this while looked upon my ſelf and all that were in our <hi>congregational way,</hi> as the only <hi>Saints</hi> of the <hi>moſt High,</hi> ſeparated from the reſt of the world by the ſtrictneſs of our <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>Purity</hi> of <hi>Ordinances</hi> and <hi>Church-Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations,</hi> and that I <hi>judged</hi> thoſe who joyned not with us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96787:8"/>
either as the <hi>Prophane Rabble</hi> of the world, or at the beſt, but as a company of <hi>Carnal, Moral</hi> and <hi>Formal Perſons;</hi> yet that <hi>many of us,</hi> by our <hi>Practiſes,</hi> in reference to the publick Affairs of the Common-wealth, and to our righteous Adminiſtrations in order thereunto, have not only <hi>fallen</hi> very <hi>ſhort</hi> of many of thoſe whom we have thus <hi>cenſured,</hi> but have <hi>acted</hi> in ſuch waies that ſome <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Patriots</hi> that knew not God, would <hi>bluſh</hi> and be <hi>aſhamed</hi> of.</p>
            <p>Ye may peradventure look upon this as a very <hi>uncharitable,</hi> or at leaſt a very <hi>unſeaſonable paſſage,</hi> from a <hi>Friend,</hi> in this day of our <hi>calamity:</hi> But if you do conſider what I have already <hi>ſpoken</hi> to ye <hi>amongſt the reſt,</hi> wherein I <hi>ſincerely</hi> diſcover the <hi>reaſon</hi> of my <hi>plain dealing;</hi> and if God hath <hi>awakened</hi> any of you (by his <hi>ſtupendious</hi> and <hi>amazing</hi> Providential Diſpenſations) as I hope he hath <hi>done many,</hi> who for theſe <hi>late years</hi> have been faſt <hi>aſleep,</hi> and have had many <hi>Golden Dreams</hi> of being <hi>Godly in Chriſt Jeſus without ſuffering,</hi> and of <hi>ruling others,</hi> while our Luſts <hi>ruled us,</hi> you will be of another <hi>mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do profeſs <hi>unfeignedly,</hi> that were our <hi>miſcarriages</hi> to be <hi>conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> I ſhould as <hi>David</hi> in another caſe, <hi>admoniſh</hi> all that have any <hi>reſpect</hi> to the <hi>Honour</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that they <hi>tell them not in Gath, that they publiſh them not in the ſtreets of Askelon, leſt the Daughters of the uncircumciſed rejoyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas! our ſinful and <hi>irregular actings</hi> for theſe <hi>late years,</hi> have been committed in the <hi>ſight</hi> of the <hi>Sun.</hi> They are like the <hi>ſins</hi> of <hi>Judah, written with a Pen of Iron, with the point of a Diamond,</hi> they are <hi>recorded</hi> in the ſeveral <hi>Declarations</hi> and <hi>Remonſtrances</hi> of the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> In the firſt and ſecond Part of the <hi>Hiſtory of Independency,</hi> and ſuch other <hi>Books</hi> of that nature which now walk abroad without <hi>Controul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now while I am ſpeaking of <hi>Books,</hi> I cannot but tell you of that which ſhould be a very cutting <hi>Conſideration,</hi> and ſhould deeply <hi>humble us;</hi> That although in that <hi>hour of Temptation,</hi> that power of darkneſs we were under, ſome of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian Party,</hi> by their <hi>publick addreſſes</hi> in Print, did patheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally diſwade from, and bear witneſs againſt thoſe <hi>unwarrantable waies,</hi> into which ſome of us were <hi>running</hi> in a full <hi>Career,</hi> in <hi>Anno,</hi> 1648. Yet <hi>amongſt</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> I do not find any <hi>diſſent</hi> or <hi>diſswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> from them <hi>publiſhed</hi> to the <hi>world,</hi> by any of our <hi>Congregational Party;</hi> but rather ſuch <hi>Books</hi> as did <hi>juſtifie</hi> and <hi>approve</hi> the ſame:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96787:8"/>
Excepting what was written by Mr. <hi>William Sedgwick,</hi> in his Book called <hi>Juſtice upon the Armies Remonſtrance,</hi> Wherein were many <hi>Paſſages,</hi> which would we have <hi>hearkened</hi> unto, as coming from an <hi>intimate friend,</hi> might have prevented thoſe <hi>woful confuſions</hi> and <hi>revolutions</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> that have ſince befallen the <hi>Nation;</hi> and that <hi>reproach</hi> that is come upon <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he as ſoon fell from thoſe ſerious <hi>convictions</hi> he tendred to our <hi>Party:</hi> And by his Book called <hi>A new View of the Armies Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance,</hi> which he made to <hi>iſſue</hi> out after the other, <hi>unſaith</hi> what in his <hi>Book aforeſaid</hi> he had preſented in many paſſages thereof.</p>
            <p>I wiſh from my ſoul that we had <hi>hearkned</hi> to thoſe many <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Counſels</hi> that were given us in <hi>thoſe daies:</hi> And that although we could not through <hi>prejudice</hi> receive them from the <hi>Parties</hi> above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named, yet that we might have <hi>conſidered</hi> what our <hi>Friend</hi> in <hi>Juſtice upon the Armies Remonſtrance</hi> ſaid unto us. But though it be too <hi>late</hi> in reference to <hi>what is paſt, yet</hi> that we may not <hi>through</hi> the <hi>high opinion</hi> that we have of <hi>our own waies,</hi> as to the <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Juſtice</hi> of them; that all <hi>others</hi> have been <hi>injurious to us,</hi> and we are the only <hi>innocents of this Iſland:</hi> Which as I have ſaid before, is the great <hi>impediment</hi> to that <hi>Moderation</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Condeſcention</hi> which I deſire may be amongſt us.</p>
            <p>That we may no longer I ſay, perſiſt in the <hi>Juſtification</hi> of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> for what is paſt, and <hi>deſiſt</hi> from any further <hi>endeavours</hi> of interrupting the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Settlement</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations</hi> for the time to come; that we may be <hi>delivered</hi> from thoſe <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>deſtructive Principles</hi> to all <hi>Civil Government,</hi> which many of us are <hi>infected with;</hi> that we may not too much <hi>deject</hi> our ſelves at theſe our <hi>preſent diſappointments,</hi> as if now a <hi>Knife</hi> were put to the <hi>Throat</hi> of the <hi>Publick Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> as ſome have ſpoken in <hi>plain Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall preſent you with ſome <hi>remarkable paſſages,</hi> in our afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Author, <hi>Juſtice upon the Armies Remonſtrance,</hi> which may be of <hi>ſingular uſe</hi> to us, for thoſe <hi>ends</hi> and <hi>purpoſes</hi> aforeſaid: Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering they come from <hi>one,</hi> who is neither of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall begin with what I <hi>named</hi> laſt, in the firſt <hi>Place,</hi> as <hi>being</hi> that which I find doth moſt <hi>perplex</hi> our Spirits: That now by the <hi>Current</hi> of the times, the <hi>publick Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> for which we have ſo long <hi>contended</hi> in our late wars againſt <hi>the King</hi> and <hi>his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96787:9"/>
Family,</hi> is like to fall to the <hi>ground;</hi> and our <hi>Government</hi> by a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> to return to <hi>King-ſhip</hi> again in the ſame <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to <hi>undeceive us,</hi> and deliver us from this <hi>fundamental er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</hi> conſider what Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> ſaith, in his <hi>Juſtice upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Remonſtrance,</hi> p. 22. ſaith he, <hi>In the propoſing of ſuch an Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt as ye hold forth to be the ground of the Quarrel</hi> (namely the things before expreſſed) <hi>ye lie groſſely: For theſe things as ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them, were never thought of in the beginning of the Quarrel: Yea, the Parliament, and we alſo proteſted to the contrary; never to alter the Government, never to alter the Fundamental Laws; yea, to protect and defend the Kings Perſon,</hi> &amp;c. For ſaith he, <hi>p. 9. That which ye offer is not the publick Intereſt, but your own particular Intereſt. It is very clear that this is not half the Intereſt of the Kingdom; tis much too narrow for a rich, honourable Nation. Generally ye know the people of England deſire Peace, Setled Religion, Eſtabliſhed Truth, Freedom of Trade, and this with his Majeſty, their King, that he may Govern them according to their honeſt and known Lawes, that they may live in Proſperity and Honour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For your deviſed things ye propoſe, the people know them not, and leſs affect, than know them.</hi> They are <hi>invented only to pleaſe and ſecure your ſelves. And to pull down Monarchy, ye are but a part: And alas! <hi>an Inconſiderable Part</hi> of the Kingdom; not one of an Hundred will own what ye ſet down for the Publick Intereſt; a diſeaſed Part ye are, a Bone ſtarted out of his place, a Piece of Timber gone from the whole Frame of the Kingdom, which is large, and conſiſteth of King, Lords and Commons, with innumerable excellent Branches that grow from theſe.</hi> Further, <hi>p. 11. This is a great fault that ye all along carry the Publick Intereſt in oppoſition to the King; which is a wicked thing, to divide them which God hath joyned; wherein ye indeed deſtroy and mangle not only the Kingdom, but the Word Intereſt; which is of a uniting ſignification;</hi> Intereſſe <hi>is to be in or amongſt each other. The Publick hath his Intereſt in the King, and the King his Intereſt in the Publick; for they have the ſame</hi> Eſſe <hi>or Intereſt, which is to be in each other: The King is in the People, and the People in the King. And though,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ye will disjoyn your ſelves from Kings, God will not, who is the King of Kings, neither will I.</hi> And therefore as he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, <hi>p. 44. It is the Peoples right to have a King.</hi> So of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf he ſaith, <hi>I confeſs it is my Birth-right to have relation to a King,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96787:9"/>
and if I am denied it, I am denied my native right.</hi> And ſaith he in the ſame page, <hi>For the King againſt whom ye go in full cry, I have this to ſay to check your violent courſe, That he had and hath a true lawfull right in the Kingdom, and to the Kingdom, and as good as any man hath to any thing he poſſeſſeth: His Crown, Revenue and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is as truly his Birthright and inheritance, as another mans houſe or lands; and he that denieth this is wilfully blind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe quotations do ſufficiently <hi>evidence,</hi> how much we have been <hi>miſtaken,</hi> and that the <hi>publick intereſt</hi> hath not been driven on, whatever hath been <hi>pretended.</hi> But becauſe I find that many of us are dull, and ſlow of heart to believe it; Out of my unfained deſire that you may lie under the ſame <hi>Convictions</hi> I now do my ſelf, as to this <hi>particular,</hi> I ſhall preſent you with a <hi>paſſage</hi> out of the ſaid Author, which ſpeaketh very plain Engliſh. Saith he, Pag. 23. <hi>I muſt deal plainly with you and my ſelf too, it is ſo groſſe that it cannot be concealed, That we had</hi> Deſigns <hi>of</hi> Particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt <hi>and advantage when we began the</hi> Warre (therefore the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt of the Nation hath been but a pretence.) <hi>There was this in our minds, and hath been in our minds continually. That the</hi> King <hi>and his party were wicked men, and not worthy and fit for their places and power they had. And that we were the Saints, the Godly, and they did properly belong to us. That the Saints are to have the high places of the earth; and that now is the time for theſe things to be performed, and that no body is now fit to adminiſter Juſtice, to rule over men but our ſelves. And therefore we were</hi> alwaies <hi>glad of any of the Kings waies that tended to difference and breach; Glad when he left his Parliament, and took Armes, thinking he was run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to his own deſtruction, that he would ſplit himſelf and his party by it; and that we ſhould have the ſpoil of them, and have an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to obtain our ends. And though we complained of the Kings obſtinacy, really we have been alwaies glad of it, becauſe that it led to his deſtruction. And the Kings not yielding at this time ye know was thirſted after by us,</hi> (meaning at the time of the Treaty in the Iſle of <hi>Wight.) And ye would not ſtir</hi> (by force to ſeclude the <hi>major</hi> part of the Members out of the Houſe of Commons, and ſo to interrupt the Treaty) <hi>till the</hi> King <hi>manifeſted a willing mind to</hi> accommodation; <hi>Peace being</hi> alwaies <hi>held deſtructive to our ends, or the recovery of our rights the whole Kingdom; for we think our ſelves the only true Lords, unleſſe the King would take part with us,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96787:10"/>
and become one of our Saints.</hi> And that this was all the change of heart was expected, appeareth by another paſſage of our Author aforeſaid, that ſpeaketh to purpoſe indeed, Pag. 27. <hi>Ye ſay the Kings heart is not changed,</hi> to which <hi>I anſwer, Ye expect that he ſhould</hi> turn <hi>not to</hi> God, <hi>but to your</hi> ſelves, <hi>to your own</hi> form <hi>of Religion and Government; and cannot account any thing a</hi> change, <hi>but yielding to your own</hi> Way, <hi>Which if he ſhould he would be ſeven times more the child of the devil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May other <hi>paſſages</hi> to this purpoſe I might have <hi>collected</hi> out of the ſaid <hi>Book;</hi> but theſe I hope will now <hi>undeceive</hi> ſuch of us as have been <hi>plain hearted,</hi> and did believe what was with much <hi>confidence</hi> affirmed, That the Cauſe which of late years hath been <hi>pleaded</hi> for <hi>ſince the Interruption of the Treaty,</hi> was for the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> that the <hi>Liberties</hi> of all <hi>Gods people</hi> were <hi>imbarqued</hi> therein: <hi>Especially</hi> conſidering who maketh this <hi>diſcovery</hi> of theſe <hi>private, ungodly deſigns,</hi> which have from the <hi>beginning</hi> been <hi>driven</hi> on by many that look upon themſelves as the only <hi>Saints. One,</hi> as I have ſaid before, neither of the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian party.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let therefore the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of theſe particular <hi>paſſages,</hi> not only <hi>humble</hi> us <hi>deeply</hi> for what is paſt, but <hi>rectifie</hi> our <hi>judgements</hi> for the time to <hi>come,</hi> incline us to the publick <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>ſettlement</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and free us from thoſe <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>deſtructive principles</hi> to all <hi>Civil Government;</hi> with which many of us I fear (by what I have obſerved) are leavened and corrupted.</p>
            <p>And to this <hi>purpoſe</hi> I ſhall from all theſe before <hi>recited collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> lay before you theſe undeniable Concluſions, flowing from the <hi>premiſes aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt <hi>Concluſion</hi> then that I deſire you to obſerve with me from the <hi>Collections</hi> aforeſaid, is this, That the <hi>Good Old Cauſe</hi> in which we firſt <hi>engaged</hi> with the <hi>Parliament,</hi> was to <hi>preſerve,</hi> and not to <hi>ſubvert</hi> the Fundamental Lawes and Government of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to <hi>protect</hi> and <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Kings Perſon</hi> and Family, and not to <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſtroy</hi> the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Publick Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> conſiſteth in being governed by their <hi>King,</hi> according to their <hi>known Lawes,</hi> and that this is their <hi>Birth-right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That the <hi>Crown-Revenue</hi> and <hi>Dignity</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> are as <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly</hi> his <hi>Birth-right,</hi> as any other mans Houſe or Lands are his.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96787:10"/>4. That to divide <hi>between</hi> the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of the <hi>Publick</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> (terming it only the Intereſt of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> as we have done of late years) is a very <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That to <hi>change</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> into a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> was to <hi>pervert</hi> that <hi>righteous Cauſe</hi> in which we firſt <hi>engaged;</hi> and was an <hi>invention</hi> to <hi>ſecure</hi> a <hi>guilty Party,</hi> and altogether againſt the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt</hi> of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That the real or ſuppoſed <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of a <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> is no <hi>Scripture</hi> Ground for thoſe who are, or do <hi>profeſs</hi> themſelves to be more <hi>holy,</hi> to <hi>uſurp Dominion</hi> over them, and to get the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> into their <hi>own hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The five former <hi>Propoſitions</hi> our aforeſaid <hi>Author</hi> hath expreſſed in <hi>Terms,</hi> and may be <hi>plentifully</hi> confirmed by the ſeveral <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> our ſeveral Oaths and Obligations, and by the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> which was ſo <hi>generally taken,</hi> by the <hi>known Lawes</hi> of the Land, and many other <hi>waies beſides.</hi> But this ſixth and laſt being only <hi>declared</hi> as a <hi>Principle</hi> upon which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny took occaſion from the <hi>Differences</hi> between <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> to <hi>act</hi> thus deſperately, to the <hi>ruine both of Prince</hi> and <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Becauſe as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> ſaith, <hi>there was this in our minds, that the King and his Party were wicked, and ſo unworthy of the places and power, and we were the Saints,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being through mercy <hi>converted</hi> from this <hi>deſtructive Principle</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> with which many of us are more or leſs <hi>corrupted;</hi> beſides the <hi>fifth Monarchy men,</hi> in whom it <hi>reignes:</hi> I <hi>hold</hi> it my Duty to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> my <hi>Brethren</hi> againſt the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Contagion</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>That therefore which I meekly offer to your <hi>Conſideration,</hi> is this:</p>
            <p>That this aforeſaid <hi>Principle</hi> of invading the <hi>Rights</hi> either of <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> becauſe <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> is expreſly againſt the <hi>written Word of God,</hi> in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> contrary to the <hi>Examples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> of the <hi>Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of all <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> and derives its <hi>Pedigree</hi> and <hi>Original</hi> from the <hi>Devil</hi> and that <hi>Roman Antichriſt,</hi> which we <hi>profeſs</hi> ſo much to <hi>hate</hi> and <hi>abhor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this you ſhall <hi>find</hi> at large <hi>proved</hi> by that <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Holy man</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">In an Aſſize Sermon of his preached above 30 years ſince, bound up in his Works.</note> Mr. <hi>Robert Bolton,</hi> who being dead, <hi>yet ſpeaketh,</hi> fully againſt this <hi>wretched Principle:</hi> Wherein you ſhall <hi>find</hi> that <hi>Bellarmine,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96787:11"/>
Father Bennet,</hi> and other of that <hi>Jeſuitical</hi> Party and <hi>Popiſh Crew</hi> were the <hi>Founders</hi> and <hi>Authors</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>I ſhall only add, that our <hi>Saviour</hi> (whoſe Diſciples we all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs our ſelves to be) when he <hi>commanded</hi> us to <hi>give</hi> to <hi>Caeſar, the things which are Caeſars,</hi> doth plainly <hi>evidence,</hi> that <hi>Caeſar</hi> (which was the Name, by which all thoſe <hi>Pagan Princes</hi> and <hi>Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors</hi> were called) they had (notwithſtanding their Impiety) their dues and rights, which did belong to them, and we are all commanded and enjoyned to give to them their rights and dues: But to take their Rights and Dues away from them, upon the<note place="margin">A warning piece for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> eſpecially for <hi>London,</hi> in the famous Hyſtory of the frantick Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1642.</note> 
               <hi>pretence</hi> of their <hi>Impiety</hi> or our <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> is to be found no where, but in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of <hi>John of Leyden,</hi> who with his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> whilſt the <hi>City of Munſter</hi> the Prime <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> was beſieged, out of which they had driven many of the Inhabitants, <hi>without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of age or ſex, running throughout the Streets in Troops, crying out, Get ye hence all ye wicked, if ye mean to ſave your lives,</hi> p. 9. <hi>They alſo publiſhed a Book called the Reſtitution, wherein they affirmed this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, That Chriſt ſhall have a Kingdom here upon earth before the Day of Judgment, wherein only the Godly and Elect ſhall reign, the wicked being every where deſtroyed; That it is lawful for the people to caſt off their Governours: And although the Apoſtles had no ſecular Jurisdiction, yet the Miniſters of their Church had power from God to uſe the Civil ſword, and by force to ſet up a new Common-wealth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Whoſe Dreams and Dotage,</hi> ſaith my Author, were <hi>confuted by many Learned men, Melancton, Juſtus Menius,</hi> and <hi>Urbanus Regius, whoſe Writings are extant,</hi> p. 15. The Holy <hi>Word of God</hi> either in the <hi>Old or New</hi> Teſtament giving ſo little <hi>ground</hi> for this <hi>Principle,</hi> and the <hi>practiſes</hi> that iſſue from it, that <hi>Thomas Muncer</hi> the <hi>Ringleader</hi> of all that <hi>uproar</hi> and <hi>Confuſion</hi> that <hi>Germany</hi> was <hi>involv'd</hi> in about <hi>Anno</hi> 1525. is forced to pretend to <hi>Divine Revelations</hi> for it, and by this <hi>ſeduced</hi> his Followers, <hi>That he had received a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand from God to kill and root up all wicked Princes and Magiſtrates, and to chuſe better in their places,</hi> p. 2.</p>
            <p>But as our Bleſſed Saviour hath commanded us to <hi>give</hi> to Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and Heathen <hi>Caeſars</hi> or Kings their <hi>Due,</hi> by way of <hi>Reverence, Subjection</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> to ſupport their <hi>Authority,</hi> ſo well knowing how <hi>backward</hi> many that profeſſed themſelves to be his Followers, would be to it, and how <hi>forward</hi> the enemies of his Goſpel, would be to calumniate his Diſciples <hi>unjuſtly,</hi> as we find
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96787:11"/>
they did his <hi>Followers,</hi> Acts 17. 17. for ſuch as <hi>did act and were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedient to the decrees of Caeſar,</hi> he therefore giveth us a <hi>Preſident</hi> for our <hi>Imitation:</hi> ſhewing how exceeding <hi>tender</hi> he was in this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to avoid all <hi>appearance</hi> of any ſuch <hi>practiſe</hi> as might flow from this <hi>Principle.</hi> Therefore ſaith he, <hi>leſt we ſhould offend them,</hi> leſt they ſhould take ſcandal at our refuſal of what was required for <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſars Maintenance,</hi> he worketh a <hi>Miracle,</hi> ſaith he to <hi>Peter, Go thou to the Sea and caſt thy Hook, and take up the fiſh that firſt cometh, and in his mouth thou ſhalt find a piece of ſilver, this take, and give them for me and thee,</hi> Mat. 17. 27.</p>
            <p>The ſame <hi>mind that was in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> was alſo in his Bleſſed <hi>Apoſtles.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>Scandals</hi> that might be <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi> or <hi>given</hi> by the <hi>Saints ſcattered throughout the world,</hi> knowing the enemies of the Goſpel were apt to <hi>ſpeak evil of them as evil doers,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 12. <hi>adviſeth</hi> them <hi>by well doing to put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh men.</hi> But how this ſhould be <hi>done,</hi> he tels us, <hi>v. 13, 14. By ſubmitting your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether to the King, as Supream; or to Governours, as thoſe which are ſent by him,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Apoſtle Paul</hi> in ſtead of <hi>directing</hi> the Godly to <hi>depoſe</hi> or <hi>oppoſe</hi> their <hi>Kings, Governours,</hi> and ſuch as were in <hi>Authority,</hi> that they being ſuppreſſed as <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> they might then <hi>lead a quiet and peaceable life in all Godlineſs,</hi> &amp;c. He adviſeth them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of making <hi>Inſurrections,</hi> to make <hi>Interceſſions,</hi> to be much in Prayer and <hi>Supplications</hi> for them: And that it ſeems is the <hi>Scripture way</hi> of procuring <hi>peaceable</hi> and <hi>quiet times,</hi> with all <hi>Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and <hi>Honeſty</hi> under their <hi>Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> evidence, that they which are <hi>Saints,</hi> have no warrant from them to invade the <hi>rights</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> to <hi>rule,</hi> but threaten <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> againſt them, with <hi>Damnation,</hi> Rom. 13.</p>
            <p>So that they have as <hi>little</hi> to invade the <hi>rights</hi> of their <hi>Fellow-Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects</hi> upon the ſame <hi>account,</hi> that they are <hi>Prophane, Wicked</hi> and <hi>Ungodly:</hi> And that therefore we may impoſe a <hi>Government</hi> upon them, to which they have no <hi>Inclination,</hi> and by <hi>Sequeſtration</hi> take away their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> if they will not <hi>comply</hi> with us therein. For God hath ſet a <hi>double Hedge</hi> about their <hi>Propriety, viz.</hi> the <hi>Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Law</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> and the <hi>Moral Law</hi> of the <hi>Lord.</hi> All the <hi>Commandments</hi> of the Second <hi>Table</hi> being as a <hi>Fence</hi> ſet about his <hi>Right</hi> to Rule, <hi>Govern</hi> and be <hi>Governed</hi> according to <hi>Law,</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96787:12"/>
5. about his <hi>Life,</hi> Com. 6. about his <hi>Estate,</hi> Com. 8. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his <hi>Good Name,</hi> Com. 9. And that nothing that doth <hi>belong to him,</hi> be ſo much as <hi>coveted</hi> or <hi>unlawfully deſired</hi> by us, Com. 10.</p>
            <p>And to <hi>conclude,</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth expreſly <hi>characterize</hi> thoſe for wicked and <hi>ungodly men,</hi> that are <hi>injurious</hi> to others in any of theſe <hi>Particulars,</hi> Job 16. 10, 11. Pſal. 73. 12. Jud. 15. and in many other places, where we ſhall <hi>find,</hi> that not only thoſe that <hi>ſwear</hi> and <hi>take Gods Name</hi> in vain, and other waies <hi>violate</hi> the <hi>Firſt Table,</hi> are pronounced impious and <hi>ungodly;</hi> but ſo alſo are thoſe which <hi>break</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> in reference to our <hi>Neighbours Rights</hi> and <hi>Proprieties,</hi> and therefore ſuch cannot then be <hi>Saints themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Objections</hi> which are made againſt the <hi>Scriptures</hi> I have <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged,</hi> which require <hi>obedience</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> as <hi>Supream,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi>condemns</hi> the doctrine of <hi>depoſing, dethroning,</hi> and <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering</hi> of <hi>Kings,</hi> becauſe <hi>wicked</hi> and <hi>ungodly,</hi> or Hereticks, as the Papiſts phraſe it; I ſay the <hi>Objections</hi> which are made againſt <hi>them,</hi> by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and other <hi>Popiſh</hi> Authors, from whence thoſe that write in the <hi>defence</hi> and juſtification of what hath been acted ſince the <hi>Treaty</hi> at the <hi>Iſle of Wight,</hi> had their main Arguments, you may find them anſwered by Mr. <hi>Robert Bolton</hi> in his <hi>Sermon</hi> before the <hi>Judges,</hi> pag. 15. where you will find their <hi>impiety</hi> and <hi>ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city</hi> fully demonſtrated, to which I <hi>refer you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pardon me I beſeech you that I have been ſo long upon this laſt <hi>Concluſion,</hi> for I now look upon this <hi>principle</hi> as that which hath been the <hi>Principal</hi> cauſe of that <hi>confuſion</hi> which hath befallen this Land of our Nativity.</p>
            <p>And thus now having by the <hi>Collections</hi> and the <hi>Concluſions</hi> drawn from them, made it <hi>evident,</hi> That we have <hi>deceived</hi> our ſelves, and ſhall <hi>deceive</hi> others, if we ſtill <hi>perſiſt</hi> in making the <hi>particular</hi> private <hi>deſigns</hi> of ſome in <hi>ſubverting</hi> the <hi>Antient Government</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> to be the <hi>concernment</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> which as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> ſaith, is <hi>large,</hi> and <hi>conſiſteth</hi> of <hi>King, Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and that if <hi>Monarchy</hi> be reſtored, and that in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily</hi> of our late <hi>King,</hi> this is not to Apoſtatize from the <hi>Cauſe</hi> in which we firſt ingaged: For we <hi>find</hi> M. <hi>Sedgwick affirming,</hi> who ever ſaith <hi>ſo, doth lie groſſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it ſhould be <hi>objected,</hi> What are all theſe quotations to us of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:96787:12"/>
the <hi>Gathered Churches</hi> to the <hi>Independent Party.</hi> Theſe particular <hi>Paſſages</hi> are charged by Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> only upon ſome of the <hi>Army,</hi> that were <hi>guilty,</hi> but they <hi>belong</hi> not to us.</p>
            <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> I wiſh from my <hi>very ſoul</hi> they did not.</p>
            <p>But I <hi>beſeech</hi> you bear with my <hi>plain dealing,</hi> and let us all lay our <hi>hands</hi> upon our <hi>hearts,</hi> and make a ſerious <hi>reflexion</hi> upon our <hi>ſelves.</hi> The <hi>Eye</hi> that <hi>ſeeth</hi> all other <hi>things,</hi> cannot <hi>ſee</hi> it ſelf but by <hi>reflexion:</hi> and we that can <hi>ſee</hi> and <hi>highly aggravate</hi> the <hi>Moats</hi> that are in the <hi>eye</hi> of others, cannot ſee the <hi>Beams</hi> that are in our own, without a due <hi>reflexion</hi> upon, and a ſincere <hi>inſpection</hi> into our <hi>ſelves.</hi> It is that which of <hi>neceſſity</hi> muſt go before <hi>Repentance,</hi> even <hi>Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration</hi> before <hi>Converſion,</hi> Pſal. 119. <hi>I conſidered my waies, and turned my feet,</hi> &amp;c. Now therefore let me entreat you to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nation</hi> being as I have ſaid before, divided into <hi>three Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> which of them have longeſt <hi>perſiſted</hi> in thoſe waies that Mr. <hi>Sedgwick chargeth</hi> upon the <hi>Army,</hi> and in the juſtification of them, which of our <hi>Gathered Churches</hi> declared the <hi>trouble</hi> of our hearts, and our great <hi>diſlike</hi> of the Armies <hi>diſobedience</hi> to the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> that <hi>raiſed</hi> them; that <hi>bewailed</hi> the great <hi>ſeverity,</hi> and <hi>John of Leyden-like cruelty</hi> they afterwards exerciſed: <hi>when fire came out of the Bramble, and conſumed the Cedars of Lebanon,</hi> which of us <hi>profeſſed</hi> with Holy <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen. 49. 6, 7. <hi>Into their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret let not my Soul come, my Glory be not thou joyned with their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly: Curſed be their wrath, for it was fierce, their anger, for it was cruel:</hi> But rather <hi>bleſſed them</hi> and <hi>God</hi> for it, <hi>joyning</hi> with them in daies of <hi>Rejoycing</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> accounting the other <hi>Parties</hi> refuſing, but <hi>old</hi> and <hi>new Malignants.</hi> I deſire you alſo to <hi>conſider</hi> what <hi>Party</hi> have enriched themſelves with the <hi>ſpoil,</hi> which Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> ſpeaketh of: That have as I ſaid before, not only bid the <hi>Army, God ſpeed,</hi> and ſo are <hi>partakers of all their evil deeds,</hi> but have <hi>joyned</hi> with them, and have <hi>owned</hi> them in all thoſe woful <hi>changes</hi> and <hi>Revolutions</hi> that our eyes have <hi>ſeen,</hi> we have been for all <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> but the <hi>right</hi> (except a few <hi>fifth Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy men</hi> that are only for <hi>King Jeſus</hi>) We have been for a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> without <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords;</hi> for a <hi>Protector</hi> and his <hi>Son,</hi> for a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> again, and then for that moſt <hi>dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Committee of Safety,</hi> erected by the <hi>Souldiery,</hi> that did ſo much <hi>threaten</hi> the <hi>Ruine</hi> and <hi>Eradication</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtracy</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96787:13"/>
of this <hi>Nation,</hi> and laſt of all, for the <hi>laſt Sediment</hi> of the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons;</hi> alſo many of us <hi>unnaturally</hi> complying with them in their <hi>horrid violence</hi> upon the <hi>City,</hi> for <hi>declaring</hi> for a <hi>free Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which <hi>Free Parliament</hi> alſo, how much we have ſhewed our <hi>averſneſs:</hi> and how well we have wiſhed to Col. <hi>Lambert</hi> and his <hi>Party,</hi> whom many of us <hi>hoped</hi> would <hi>interrupt</hi> their <hi>Meeting</hi> together, is <hi>notorious</hi> to the world, otherwiſe I ſhould not have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſo <hi>freely</hi> thereunto.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore upon theſe <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> take <hi>ſhame</hi> to our ſelves, get our <hi>proud</hi> hearts <hi>humbled,</hi> our <hi>Soules ſoftned,</hi> our <hi>Spirits cooled,</hi> the heates and <hi>animoſities</hi> of our minds <hi>abated,</hi> and make all our harſh <hi>cenſuring, judging</hi> and <hi>accuſing</hi> of others, to <hi>terminate</hi> in the <hi>accuſing, judging</hi> and <hi>condemning</hi> of our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us in <hi>theſe dayes,</hi> wherein of late we have ſeen our ſelves ſo much <hi>neglected</hi> by the <hi>Nation,</hi> ſo <hi>few</hi> of us being put either into the <hi>Militia</hi> in <hi>City</hi> or <hi>Country;</hi> or by the people of this <hi>Nation,</hi> choſen for their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> let us be ſo far from <hi>cenſuring</hi> and <hi>judging</hi> of them for <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>ungodly</hi> in ſo <hi>doing</hi> (imputing it only to the enmity that is in the hearts of all unrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate and unconverted men to the power of Godlineſs) But let us who have ſo much denied the <hi>Power of it</hi> as we have done, <hi>judge</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> our <hi>ſelves,</hi> for that <hi>Cruelty, Injuſtice</hi> and <hi>Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of ours over them, of which we have given them <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> to be ſo <hi>ſenſible</hi> of for theſe many years.</p>
            <p>I do <hi>profeſs,</hi> it is that which much <hi>ſaddens</hi> my <hi>Spirit,</hi> to <hi>obſerve,</hi> that we that do <hi>profeſs</hi> our ſelves to be <hi>Saints,</hi> and to be of ſuch <hi>ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous</hi> and tender <hi>Conſciences,</hi> that in the Circumſtantials of the Worſhip of God, we will do nothing without an expreſs Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, though it be no where forbid, but all muſt be <hi>according to the Pattern in the Mount;</hi> dare not <hi>communicate</hi> with any at the <hi>Lords Table,</hi> but ſuch as we account for <hi>Saints</hi> like our ſelves, though Chriſt did with <hi>Judas;</hi> or <hi>baptize</hi> our young <hi>Infants,</hi> becauſe we find no expreſs Command for it in the New <hi>Teſtament.</hi> Many of which Judgment renouncing the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of this <hi>Nation,</hi> as coming from the <hi>Pope,</hi> and yet that many of us ſhould carry on the <note n="*" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Strongs</hi> Serm. Preached at <hi>Pauls</hi> Nov. 5. 1653. <hi>Pag.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Papiſts deſigns</hi> all this while, and act from their <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> againſt <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> becauſe Hereticks or <hi>ungodly,</hi> and go againſt the expreſs <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Preſidents</hi> of our Lord and Maſter
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96787:13"/>
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi> I ſay, this ſhould very much <hi>humble</hi> us, eſpecially to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That ſuch as make not that high <hi>Profeſſion</hi> with us, ſhould <hi>ſtumble</hi> at the <hi>Scandals</hi> we give and they take at our <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Practiſes</hi> in reference to <hi>Civil Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the <hi>Prophane</hi> Rabble of the world, Swearers, Drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards and Sabbath-breakers, Whoremongers, and ſuch like Flagitious Sinners ſhould exceed us in <hi>Loyality</hi> to our <hi>Native Prince;</hi> when as the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> even the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> is as <hi>clear</hi> and expreſs in the charging of that upon our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> as to <hi>hear,</hi> to <hi>pray,</hi> to <hi>meditate,</hi> to <hi>walk with God,</hi> and to <hi>fear</hi> his Dreadful Name. And therefore we ſhall find, that to <hi>fear God</hi> and <hi>honour the King,</hi> are joyned together by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 17. Giving us to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that the <hi>contempt</hi> of this Precept (which anſwers to the <hi>Fifth Commandment</hi>) is not only <hi>inconſiſtent</hi> with the true <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but alſo <hi>drawes</hi> after it, the <hi>Breach</hi> of all the reſt of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments</hi> of the Second Table, Rebellion, Treaſon, Regicide, Paracide, and all kind of Murder, Injuſtice, Cruelty, and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, the ſlanderous defaming and devouring of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours Good name; of all which I could wiſh, that our own times did not give too full proof and <hi>evidence</hi> of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore upon all theſe <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> be moved to the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Repentance</hi> as to theſe particular ſins: To think upon <hi>Reſtitution,</hi> without which as one of the Fathers hath it, <hi>non remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur peccatum, niſi reſtituetur ablatum:</hi> And let us be <hi>perſwaded</hi> to give over the <hi>reproaching</hi> of ſuch who are for a <hi>regulated Monarchy,</hi> that deſire the <hi>Throne</hi> may be eſtabliſhed in <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> I ſay, let us no longer <hi>revile</hi> them with the odious Name of <hi>Cavee</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant,</hi> which words ye <hi>know</hi> are frequent amongſt us, &amp; with which now we are apt to brand all that are not of our Party: Whereas if we would look into the firſt <hi>remonſtrance</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> we ſhould find the <hi>Malignant Party</hi> to be deſcribed to be ſuch as <hi>would intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce erroneous Doctrines</hi> into the Church, endeavour to <hi>ſubvert</hi> the <hi>Fundamental Lawes</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> to erect an <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary power</hi> to <hi>diſtemper</hi> the <hi>Army</hi> that then was in the <hi>North,</hi> and to bring it up to <hi>overaw the Parliament.</hi> By all which <hi>Characters,</hi> my Friends, I fear the <hi>Name</hi> doth moſt properly <hi>belong</hi> to our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And let us now get out of theſe <hi>Extreams</hi> into which we have ſo madly run, for ſome <hi>miſſe-governments</hi> in the <hi>King,</hi> to cut him
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96787:14"/>
off, and caſt off all <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> and upon <hi>ſelfiſh deſigns,</hi> to erect a <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> which Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> calleth <hi>a Hoddy Dod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> and <hi>all Breach,</hi> ſuch a one as <hi>derogates from the Majeſty of God,</hi> and the <hi>wiſdom of man.</hi> Though it had a <hi>precious Foundation,</hi> and the <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> thereof was tempered even with the <hi>Blood</hi> of all <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>men</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and of all <hi>Parties</hi> but our own, and hath <hi>conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> more <hi>Millions</hi> then <hi>any,</hi> if not all the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ever did.</p>
            <p>I ſay, let us be <hi>weaned</hi> from this <hi>Novelty;</hi> and now let our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits be reconciled to <hi>Kingly Government again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Even that <hi>Ancient Government</hi> by <hi>Kings,</hi> which oweth its <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> to the <hi>Ancient of Daies,</hi> who hath ſaid, <hi>By me Kings reign,</hi> and to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is the <hi>Lord of Lords,</hi> the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> the true <hi>Fountain of Honour:</hi> That <hi>Government</hi> by which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>promiſed</hi> in Goſpel times, that his <hi>Church</hi> ſhall be <hi>provided</hi> for, and <hi>protected;</hi> that <hi>Kings ſhall be their Fathers, and Queens their Nurſing Mothers:</hi> That <hi>Government</hi> in the want of which, we have <hi>found</hi> by <hi>experience</hi> all thoſe <hi>wickedneſſes perpetrated</hi> as were done in <hi>thoſe daies, when there was no King in Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 17. 6. &amp; 19. 1. That <hi>Ancient way of Government</hi> by which <hi>God</hi> ruled his people of <hi>old,</hi> even by <hi>Moſes,</hi> who was <hi>King in Jeſurun,</hi> and by which this <hi>Nation</hi> hath been <hi>Governed</hi> for many hundred years, and never by a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> before.</p>
            <p>I ſay, let us by theſe <hi>Arguments</hi> ſhake hands and be friends again with <hi>Kingly Government,</hi> with which we have been at <hi>odds</hi> theſe many years.</p>
            <p>And to bring us <hi>together again,</hi> I ſhall to theſe <hi>Arguments</hi> give you one <hi>Quotation</hi> more from our Friend Mr. <hi>Sedgwick;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>P. 11. Kinglineſs agreeth with all Chriſtians, they who are of a Royal Nature, and made Kings with Chriſt, cannot but be Friends to it. It is a Baſtard Religion that is inconſiſtent with the Majeſty and Greatneſs of the moſt abſolute Monarch: And ſuch Spirits are ſtrangers from the Kingdom of Heaven, and know not the Glory in which God liveth, and are of narrow and evil minds, that are corrupt themſelves and not able to bear Greatneſs, and ſo think God cannot or will not qualifie men for ſuch high Places, with anſwerable and proportionable Goodneſs and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In my <hi>mind</hi> there is very much of <hi>Truth</hi> in this <hi>Quotation,</hi> and I <hi>wiſh</hi> he be of the ſame <hi>mind</hi> ſtill that then uttered it. Without
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:96787:14"/>
all <hi>doubt,</hi> they which know any thing of the waies of <hi>Gods admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations,</hi> either in the <hi>Kingdom of Grace</hi> or of <hi>Glory,</hi> ſhould not be of <hi>Anti-monarchical</hi> Spirits. Their <hi>Spirits</hi> as he ſaith, are <hi>narrow,</hi> their <hi>Minds</hi> are <hi>evil:</hi> Eſpecially thoſe amongſt us who have load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſuch <hi>reproaches, him</hi> whom I am apt to <hi>believe</hi> the <hi>Divine Providence</hi> hath ſo wonderfully preſerved to <hi>rule theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now the very naming of <hi>Providence</hi> doth furniſh me with a moſt cogent <hi>Argument</hi> in my <hi>judgment,</hi> to prevail with us all to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to what I move you.</p>
            <p>For how hath the <hi>Divine Providence overturned, overturned, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturned</hi> all the waies of <hi>Government</hi> we have attempted to ſet up <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>Right</hi> both of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick</hi> teacheth us.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſs, we have cauſe to fear we have highly offended in walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo by <hi>Providence,</hi> making that to <hi>legitimate</hi> thoſe <hi>Actions</hi> of ours, for which the <hi>Word</hi> gave no warrant, but condemned rather. This was the <hi>Argument</hi> by which we anſwered all our <hi>Oppoſers:</hi> Oh the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>declared</hi> from Heaven the <hi>juſtneſs</hi> of our <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Waies!</hi> Our <hi>Protector</hi> though in his long <hi>Speech</hi> at the <hi>Diſsolution</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> (ſo called) <hi>Jan.</hi> 22. 1654. he doth ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much in many places <hi>preſs</hi> all to obſerve the voice of <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> which had done ſuch great things, wondering that they could not proceed further to the Settlement of the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> according to his deſire, for which he broke them up: yet he was ſomwhat loath to own the <hi>Providence</hi> of God therein: For ſaith he, <hi>I cannot apprehend what it is, I would be loath to call it a Fate, that were too Paganiſh a Word, but there is ſomthing in it that we have not our expectation,</hi> P. 26. And ſure there was the <hi>Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> counter-working.</p>
            <p>But how evidently it hath appeared ſince, is our Duty as <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to own and <hi>acknowledge;</hi> eſpecially ſince this <hi>remarkeable</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in his Speech <hi>aforeſaid,</hi> P. 27. <hi>As for this Cauſe it is either of God or man: If it be of God, it will bear up; if it be of man, it will tumble, as every thing that hath been of man hath done ſince the World began: And as this is, ſo the all wiſe God deal with it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us who have made the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> our Rule, contrary to this expreſs <hi>Command</hi> amongſt others, that we <hi>ſhould do no evil that good might come of it,</hi> Let us I ſay, as becometh <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96787:15"/>
acknowledge the <hi>all-wiſe, Providential Diſpenſations</hi> in ſo <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendiouſly tumbling</hi> down the chief <hi>Actors</hi> and <hi>Agitators</hi> in thoſe <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warrantable waies,</hi> we have too too much <hi>owned</hi> and <hi>juſtified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Truly me thinks the ſtrange <hi>Tumblings</hi> that we have ſeen ſince the <hi>Protector</hi> was laid in his Grave, and how by an <hi>evil Spirit the all-wiſe God hath ſent among the</hi> men of <hi>Sechem,</hi> he hath ſo ſtrangely<note place="margin">Judg. 9. 23.</note> 
               <hi>tumbled down the Family of Abimelech,</hi> I ſay, that the neer <hi>Relations</hi> of the <hi>Old Protector</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>inſtrumental</hi> in pulling down the <hi>New One;</hi> and in that, to lay the <hi>Foundations</hi> of that <hi>Diſgrace</hi> that is come upon themſelves.</p>
            <p>And how ſtrangely the <hi>Providence</hi> of God hath brought about the <hi>Calling</hi> of this <hi>Parliament, defeated</hi> Col. <hi>Lambert</hi> ſince his eſcape, <hi>ſcattering</hi> the Diſturbers of the <hi>Nations Peace,</hi> and <hi>diſappointed</hi> their <hi>hopes</hi> of hindring the <hi>peaceable</hi> Meeting of this <hi>great Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay, theſe <hi>ſtrange</hi> and moſt <hi>admirable Providences</hi> which would fill a <hi>Volume</hi> with the Obſervations of all the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of them, ſhould now <hi>convince</hi> us, that it is <hi>hardkicking againſt the pricks,</hi> and ſhould very much bring us into a <hi>low Opinion</hi> and eſteem of our <hi>ſelves,</hi> and encline us to a <hi>peaceable</hi> and Chriſtian <hi>Accommodation</hi> with all <hi>Parties,</hi> and to ſhew forth more <hi>Moderation</hi> of mind than we have yet made known to the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is only for theſe <hi>ends</hi> that I have ſpoken ſo <hi>home,</hi> and dealt ſo <hi>impartially</hi> with you, being <hi>acquainted</hi> with the <hi>temper</hi> of many of your ſpirits which <hi>require it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if any <hi>Prophanatick</hi> ſhall make this curſed uſe of what I have written, as thereby to <hi>heighten</hi> that <hi>hatred</hi> of <hi>holineſs</hi> (that is ſo natural to all unregenerate men) or to harden himſelf in his way of wickedneſs, <hi>ſtumble</hi> and be <hi>ſcandalized</hi> at the <hi>fallings</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> I have here <hi>preſented,</hi> I ſay no more to him, but at his eternal peril be it: For though it be <hi>true</hi> which our <hi>Saviour</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>Wo be to them by whom offences come;</hi> ſo it is as true alſo, <hi>Wo be to the world</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 18. 7.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe of offences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for <hi>many</hi> of the <hi>late Kings Party,</hi> that have been the <hi>greateſt ſufferers</hi> for him, I fear not that any ſuch ill <hi>uſe</hi> ſhould be made by them; ſo <hi>many</hi> of the <hi>Nobility</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> from <hi>Somerſetſhire, North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amptonſhire, Kent,</hi> and about the <hi>City of London</hi> and other places, <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> moſt <hi>piouſly</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianly Declared,</hi> That they do <hi>reflect upon their paſt ſufferings, as proceeding from the hand of God;</hi> and that they
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:96787:15"/>
               <hi>do abhorre all revengefull thoughts</hi> or <hi>actions</hi> againſt any <hi>party</hi> or <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>Declarations</hi> of theirs have very much won my <hi>heart,</hi> and I deſire that they may have the like effect upon all of our <hi>Party,</hi> towards thoſe truly <hi>noble</hi> and <hi>gentle</hi> Perſons, who have thus preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us with their <hi>love</hi> and <hi>goodneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore no <hi>longer</hi> harbour any <hi>jealous</hi> and <hi>uncharitable ſurmiſes</hi> againſt them: Let us not ſay it is an eaſie matter to give <hi>good words,</hi> though they never intend it. The Apoſtle tels us, <hi>Love, it neither thinketh</hi> or <hi>ſpeaketh evil.</hi> But let us <hi>all</hi> who have <hi>ſeen</hi> how <hi>evil</hi> and deſtructive <hi>diviſions</hi> and <hi>contentions</hi> are amongſt <hi>Brethren;</hi> now come and <hi>ſee</hi> how <hi>good</hi> and <hi>joyfull</hi> it is for <hi>Brethren to dwell together in unity;</hi> for doubtleſs we are <hi>Brethren,</hi> and all have <hi>one Father,</hi> though we moſt <hi>unhappily</hi> like <hi>Joſephs brethren, have fallen out by the way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that this <hi>good work</hi> may be <hi>proſecuted</hi> and carried on in all our <hi>Congregations,</hi> As I have ſpoken in particular to the <hi>Epiſcopal Clergy,</hi> and to the <hi>Presbyterian Miniſters,</hi> ſo I ſhall <hi>addreſs</hi> my ſelf to ye who are the <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> of our <hi>Congregations;</hi> ſuch as <hi>labour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> being <hi>lawfully</hi> called thereunto. Oh be ye <hi>inſtant</hi> in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> and out of <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> at all <hi>times,</hi> and upon all <hi>occaſions,</hi> more <hi>frequently</hi> then ever preſſing upon your <hi>hearers,</hi> and faithfully applying to them, the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Self-denial,</hi> the want of which I fear is the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all that <hi>ſelfiſhneſſe</hi> which is in our <hi>party;</hi> which <hi>ſelfiſhneſſe</hi> is the ſumme of Vice, the <hi>capital enemy</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and the <hi>King,</hi> of <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> of all <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>vertue,</hi> of every <hi>holy Ordinance</hi> and duty, eſpecially of <hi>unity</hi> and <hi>Brotherly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>love,</hi> of the welfare of the <hi>Publick,</hi> and our own <hi>true good</hi> and eternal <hi>happineſſe.</hi> Oh therefore, let the Doctrine of <hi>Self-denial</hi> be more <hi>preached,</hi> be more <hi>practiſed</hi> then ever. Make alſo <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> of preaching more then ever againſt <hi>hypocriſie,</hi> againſt <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to the <hi>fifth Commandment.</hi> And as the moſt of your hearers profeſs themſelves to be ſuch as have the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> ſee to take heed of thoſe <hi>ungodly luſts</hi> which <hi>Jude</hi> tels us argue, <hi>v.</hi> 19. that they <hi>have not the ſpirit.</hi> And perſwade them above all things to ſhew forth in their <hi>converſations</hi> for the time to come, thoſe <hi>fruits of the ſpirit,</hi> which the Apoſtle ſpeaketh on, <hi>Eph. 5. 9. The fruit of the ſpirit is in all goodneſſe, righteouſneſſe and truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such fruits of the ſpirit as theſe breaking out in our lives and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:96787:16"/>
               <hi>converſations,</hi> will make them <hi>winning,</hi> and draw thoſe that are <hi>without</hi> to like and approve of the <hi>Religion</hi> we <hi>profeſſe.</hi> Theſe are ſuch <hi>fruits</hi> which have but little appeared to the <hi>world</hi> in theſe late years <hi>amongst</hi> us.</p>
            <p>And therefore be <hi>perſwaded</hi> and entreated to <hi>charge</hi> it upon the <hi>conſciences</hi> of your hearers, that they bring them forth. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tels us indeed of other <hi>fruits of the ſpirit,</hi> as <hi>faith, love,</hi> &amp;c. theſe do <hi>unite</hi> our <hi>ſouls</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> to us; but <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignity, an affable and charitable <hi>diſpoſition, Righteouſneſſe</hi> in our <hi>converſe</hi> and <hi>commerce</hi> in the world; <hi>Truth,</hi> veracity and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in our <hi>words</hi> and <hi>promiſes,</hi> theſe <hi>unite</hi> and <hi>tye</hi> the ſouls of men to us <hi>all; Theſe things,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> are <hi>profitable to men.</hi> All other our <hi>gracious qualifications,</hi> our moſt elevated <hi>common gifts</hi> of the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> though we could be never ſo <hi>Seraphical</hi> in our Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, though never ſo <hi>Angelical</hi> in our expreſſions, though we had the <hi>tongue of men and Angels,</hi> though we ſhould <hi>conſume</hi> our lungs by our long prayers, and even <hi>weep</hi> our ſelves <hi>blind</hi> for many of our ſins; yet ſhould theſe be <hi>abſtracted</hi> from <hi>goodneſſe, righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> which the Apoſtle calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>fruit of the ſpirit,</hi> we ſhould ſhew our ſelves to be but of a <hi>ſelfiſh</hi> and ſolitary <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> and no way allure others to be in love with <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Perſwade therefore your people to <hi>ſhun</hi> that <hi>ſupercilious</hi> moroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of many in their converſation, ſaying unto their <hi>neighbours,</hi> Stand by for I am <hi>more holy then thou;</hi> that <hi>hard-heartedneſs</hi> that commonly appeareth in many <hi>Profeſſors</hi> towards poor and indigent perſons: For though the <hi>houſhold of faith</hi> are to have the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, yet we are expreſly commanded <hi>to do good unto all;</hi> even to<note place="margin">Gal. 6. 10.</note> ſuch as upon whom our <hi>heavenly Father</hi> cauſeth his ſun to ſhine, and his rain to fall, which are <hi>the bad as well as the good.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5. 45.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> relates of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Profeſſors in his time, that they were called, not <hi>Chriſtiani,</hi> but <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>unde venit <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chrestiani,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a word which ſignifieth <hi>good, bountiful, 1 Pet. 2. 3. ſweetneſs</hi> of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and diſpoſition; <hi>profitableneſs,</hi> 2 Tim. 2. 14. and that fruit of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> Gal. 5. 22. tranſlated <hi>gentleneſs.</hi> It ſhould ſeem then they were ſuch cloſe <hi>followers</hi> of the <hi>gentleneſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> who <hi>went about doing good,</hi> and that they were ſo <hi>profitable</hi> unto <hi>humane ſociety,</hi> by their <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of diſpoſition, their <hi>gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> their <hi>bounty, benignity</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> they did ſo abound in ſuch fruits of the ſpirit, that they were called <hi>Chreſtians.</hi> Now if
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:96787:16"/>
we that live in theſe <hi>evil times,</hi> could be brought but to this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent temper, how ſhould we adorn and crown our holy <hi>profeſſion,</hi> and draw in others to a love and liking of our <hi>zeal</hi> for God in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>firſt Table,</hi> and make all our preſent <hi>diviſions</hi> to vaniſh: Eſpecially if it be in <hi>conjunction</hi> with <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> which will make us give to all their due; <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> as <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream,</hi> and to all other <hi>Governours</hi> ſent by him; and to <hi>all</hi> our <hi>equals</hi> love. By this means then ſhall all <hi>parties</hi> be <hi>united</hi> together, and the effect of theſe works of <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> ſhall be <hi>peace,</hi> and a quiet ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of theſe <hi>three Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have now but a few words to ſpeak unto ye of the <hi>Congregated Churches,</hi> in reference to the <hi>extreams</hi> into which we have run, in relation to <hi>matters of Religion</hi> and <hi>Church Government,</hi> and to preſs you to <hi>moderation</hi> therein alſo, as I have done the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> parties, and ſo I ſhall conclude my Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Though I muſt needs ſay the parties before named have not run into that <hi>extream</hi> with us, in reference to the <hi>Civil Government</hi> of the Nation, and therefore I have not had that occaſion to ſpeak to them on that ſubject which I have ſo largely inſiſted on to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Yet in <hi>Reference</hi> to <hi>Church Government,</hi> or matters of the <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> there are none of us all can waſh our hands in <hi>innocency.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What <hi>juſt occaſion</hi> was given to all truly <hi>conſcientious</hi> and pious men to be offended at the <hi>perſecutions</hi> of the <hi>Prelates,</hi> and their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious <hi>injunctions</hi> and <hi>innovations;</hi> and conſequently what need there was of a <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Church Government,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Deering,</hi> my Lord <hi>Digby,</hi> and others of their own <hi>party</hi> have decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the former quotations.</p>
            <p>But how this bleſſed work hath miſerably miſcarried in all our hands, <hi>hinc illae lachrimae.</hi> I know the <hi>Presbyterian party</hi> are apt to ſay, if we <hi>Independents</hi> had not interpoſed, this work of <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> had gon on with ſpeed, their <hi>Government</hi> had been ſetled in the Nation; not <hi>conſidering</hi> that the <hi>progreſſe</hi> that they had made <hi>therein</hi> by the <hi>ſword,</hi> would (like the Commonwealth we have been raiſing all this while) require the <hi>continuance</hi> of the ſame to ſupport and bear it up at <hi>vaſt charges:</hi> The <hi>Government</hi> aforeſaid being not only diſſatisfactory and diſpleaſing to our <hi>late King,</hi> but to the greateſt part of the <hi>Nobility,</hi> Gentry and <hi>Commons</hi> of the Land, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our <hi>ſelves;</hi> eſpecially as <hi>univerſal conformity</hi> thereunto by the <hi>Covenant</hi> was <hi>intended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to avoid theſe <hi>extreams</hi> into which we ſaw both others run
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:96787:17"/>
before us, even of a <hi>violent, abſolute</hi> and <hi>univerſal compulſion</hi> of <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity;</hi> that nothing in Matters of <hi>Religion</hi> might be urged that might go againſt our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and that according to our <hi>Principle,</hi> that <hi>particular Congregations</hi> are <hi>Independent,</hi> and ſubject to no Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from any other Church but that of <hi>non-communion.</hi> We have given a <hi>boundleſs</hi> &amp; lawleſs <hi>toleration</hi> to all <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>erroneous Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> from the <hi>Anti-Trinitarian</hi> to the <hi>Quaker,</hi> wherein though we have run into much <hi>Confuſion</hi> and Diſorder, yet have we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in come nearer to the <hi>Judgment</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> before quoted, than either the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> or <hi>Epiſcopal Party</hi> themſelves; who in his Diſcourſe about dealing with <hi>erring Chriſtians,</hi> doth neither approve of the <hi>High Commiſſion Court,</hi> or of a <hi>Covenant</hi> to ſwear down the <hi>Extirpation</hi> of <hi>Errour, Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſme</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Or any other way of ſeverity</note>. <q>For ſaith he, <hi>P. 55. Severity</hi> againſt, and ſeparation from <hi>Heretical companies,</hi> took its Beginning from the <hi>Hereticks</hi> themſelves, and if we ſearch the <hi>Stories,</hi> we ſhall find that the Church did not at the firſt ariſing, <hi>thruſt</hi> them from her, themſelves went out. And as for <hi>ſeverity,</hi> that which the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> ſometimes ſpake in their own <hi>defence, Illam eſſe veram Ecccleſiam quae perſecutionem patitur, non quaefacit,</hi> She was the <hi>true Church</hi> not which <hi>raiſed,</hi> but which ſuffered <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution,</hi> was <hi>de facto</hi> true for a great ſpace. For when <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> firſt aroſe in the <hi>Church,</hi> all kinds of <hi>violence</hi> were uſed by the <hi>erring Factions,</hi> but the Church ſeemed not for a long time to have known any uſe of a <hi>ſword,</hi> but only of a <hi>Buckler;</hi> and when ſhe began to uſe the <hi>Sword,</hi> ſome of her beſt and <hi>chiefeſt Captains</hi> much <hi>diſliked it.</hi> The firſt <hi>Law</hi> that ever was made in this kind, was enacted by <hi>Theodoſius</hi> againſt the <hi>Donatiſts;</hi> but with this <hi>reſtraint,</hi> that it ſhould <hi>extend</hi> againſt none but ſuch as were <hi>tumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous:</hi> and till that time, they were not ſo much as toucht with any <hi>mulct,</hi> though but <hi>pecuniary,</hi> til that <hi>ſhameful outrage</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt <hi>Biſhop Maximian,</hi> whom they beat down with Bats and Clubs, even as he ſtood at the <hi>Altar;</hi> ſo that not ſo much the <hi>Errour</hi> of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as their <hi>Riots</hi> and <hi>Mutinies</hi> were by <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Lawes reſtrained.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus ſar Learned, <hi>Pious</hi> and <hi>Moderate</hi> Mr. <hi>Hales,</hi> of whoſe <hi>Judgment</hi> had the <hi>Epiſcopal Party</hi> been in the time of their <hi>Government,</hi> theſe <hi>troubles</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> had never been <hi>raiſed,</hi> nor had theſe <hi>miſeries</hi> come upon the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom:</hi> And were but what he hath <hi>written,</hi> ſeriouſly pondered by <hi>conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Christians</hi> of all <hi>Parties,</hi> it would <hi>pluck up</hi> the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all our <hi>Diviſions</hi> by the <hi>roots.</hi> As I ſhall therefore <hi>commend</hi> to you <hi>all</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Who ſhall be called to adviſe about matters of Religion.</note> his <hi>Works</hi> ſet forth by Mr. <hi>Pearſon</hi> aforeſaid, ſo this one particular <hi>Paſsage</hi> more amongſt the reſt; <hi>It is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:96787:17"/>
not</hi> ſaith he, <hi>p.</hi> 54. <q>It is not the variety of <hi>Opinions,</hi> but our own <hi>perverſe wills,</hi> who think it meet that all ſhould be <hi>conceited</hi> as our <hi>ſelves</hi> are; which hath ſo <hi>inconvenienced</hi> the <hi>Church.</hi> Were we not ſo ready to <hi>anathematize</hi> each other, where we concur not in opinion, we might in <hi>hearts</hi> be <hi>united,</hi> though in our <hi>tongues</hi> we were <hi>divided,</hi> and that with <hi>ſingular profit</hi> to all <hi>ſides.</hi> It is the <hi>Unity of the Spirit in the Bond of peace,</hi> and not <hi>Identity of Conceit,</hi> which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> requireth at the hands of <hi>Christians.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhort <hi>Quotation</hi> giveth us a true <hi>account</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Cure</hi> of all our <hi>Church</hi> Diſſentions and Diviſions.</p>
            <p>Now that theſe <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Schiſms</hi> may not grow <hi>wider,</hi> but be <hi>healed</hi> up (and I hope therein <hi>offer</hi> the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of very many <hi>Church-Members</hi>) I ſay, I ſhall <hi>humbly</hi> propound this <hi>expedient:</hi> Let but the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian Parties</hi> abandon and renounce their <hi>Principle</hi> of <hi>univerſal Conformity</hi> and <hi>compulſion,</hi> and <hi>we</hi> of the <hi>Gathered Churches, ours</hi> of a <hi>univerſal toleration</hi> and liberty for <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience:</hi> They <hi>exerciſing</hi> no other <hi>compulſive power</hi> over <hi>tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> than what they are <hi>furniſhed</hi> with from the <hi>Word of God;</hi> and we <hi>expecting</hi> and requiring no other <hi>liberty</hi> from them than what the <hi>Word of God</hi> allowes us.</p>
            <p>And no doubt but we ſhall <hi>find</hi> the Son of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> ariſing upon us with <hi>healing</hi> under his <hi>wings,</hi> and give us all that <hi>unity</hi> of Spirit, which is the <hi>Bond of Peace,</hi> though we have not <hi>Identity</hi> of <hi>Conceits</hi> and <hi>Apprehenſions,</hi> and will make us all to be of <hi>one Heart,</hi> though we are not all of <hi>one mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By what way of <hi>Government</hi> this may be beſt effected, I leave to the Advice of an <hi>Aſsembly</hi> of <hi>Religious</hi> and <hi>Learned Miniſters</hi> of all <hi>Parties</hi> (whom no doubt the <hi>Parliament</hi> will ſpeedily <hi>ſummon</hi>) and to the <hi>Reſult</hi> and determinations of the <hi>Parliament</hi> thereupon, in reference to <hi>Church-matters</hi> (I hope) all ſober and <hi>moderate Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents</hi> if not very <hi>weak in judgment</hi> or ſtrongly poſſeſt with <hi>preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice,</hi> and many other corruptions <hi>therein,</hi> will humbly <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>acquieſce</hi> therein.</p>
            <p>And not only ſo, but alſo to the <hi>judgment</hi> of that great <hi>Council,</hi> in reference to what they have voted, not only of the way of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> by <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but alſo to the <hi>Government</hi> of his <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe Gratious <hi>Declaration</hi> of a <hi>free</hi> and <hi>general pardon to all his Subjects, how faulty ſoever,</hi> excepting <hi>only ſuch as ſhall be here after excepted</hi> by <hi>Parliament</hi> (which cannot now be many, conſidering the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> are gone down into the duſt.) And alſo of <hi>Liberty</hi> to <hi>tender Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>that no man ſhall be diſquieted or called in queſtion for differences of Opinion in matters of Religion, that do not diſturb the Peace of the Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96787:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>I ſay, theſe <hi>Offers</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> from his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> whom many of our <hi>Conſciences</hi> tell us we have ſo much <hi>offended,</hi> and <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed</hi> to ſuch great <hi>afflictions</hi> and <hi>Sufferings,</hi> ſhould now <hi>melt</hi> our hearts through great <hi>contrition</hi> and <hi>penitential remorſe</hi> for what is paſt, and work us to <hi>Reſolutions</hi> of all due <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> to his <hi>Government</hi> for the time to come, and that not for <hi>fear,</hi> but for <hi>Conſcience</hi> ſake.</p>
            <p>Methinks <hi>God</hi> having (as we ought to judge in Charity, by his <hi>Gracious expreſſions)</hi> turned his <hi>Royal heart</hi> towards us, how ſhould it turn our <hi>hearts</hi> to be <hi>Loyal</hi> towards Him and make us now to make good what I now <hi>believe</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by his Royal <hi>Father,</hi> in the <hi>Advice</hi> he gave to him before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, when <hi>Prince</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of <hi>Wales;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>None will be more Loyal and Faithful to you and me, than thoſe Subjects, who ſenſible of their Errours and great Injuries, ſhall feel in their own Soules moſt vehement Motives to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and earneſt deſires to make ſome reparation for their former defects.</hi> Nay, this <hi>Confidence</hi> his Late Majeſty had of his moſt offending Subjects, that he further ſaith, in the ſaid <hi>Advice, For thoſe that repent of any defect in their Duty to me, I believe ye ſhall find them truly zealous to repay with Intereſt that Loyalty and Love to</hi> You, <hi>that was due to</hi> Me.</p>
            <p>Surely by what I have ſo largely inſiſted upon in all this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, we of the <hi>Gathered Churches</hi> cannot be ſo <hi>ſtupid,</hi> but needs muſt be brought to a ſenſe of this, that we have been <hi>exceeding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective</hi> in our <hi>Duty</hi> to the <hi>Late King.</hi> The <hi>Presbyterian Party</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> about the Late <hi>Kings Death,</hi> and <hi>ſince</hi> have<note place="margin">Some of them ſuffering death and baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>teſtified</hi> their <hi>Repentance</hi> for their <hi>Defects</hi> in their <hi>Duty</hi> to the <hi>Late King,</hi> by their <hi>Loyalty</hi> to his <hi>Majeſty.</hi> Methinks we ſhould no longer lie under the ſame <hi>reproof</hi> as they did, 2 <hi>Sam. 19. 12. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are ye the laſt in bringing back the King?</hi> Well, <hi>nunquam ſera eſt ad bonosmores via.</hi> Let us therefore though we have <hi>ſet out</hi> after others, yet let us <hi>overtake</hi> them in the <hi>ſpeedy</hi> and <hi>vigorous expreſſions</hi> of our <hi>Repentance</hi> for the <hi>Defects</hi> of our Duty to the <hi>Late King,</hi> by our <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Loyalty</hi> to our preſent <hi>Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let our <hi>Contentions</hi> now be <hi>turned</hi> into this <hi>Christian emulation,</hi> which <hi>Party</hi> of us ſhall be moſt <hi>pious</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> moſt <hi>Loyal</hi> toward the <hi>King,</hi> and moſt <hi>loving</hi> to one <hi>another:</hi> And then no <hi>doubt</hi> if our <hi>waies pleaſe the Lord,</hi> he will make not only our <hi>enemies</hi> to be at <hi>peace</hi> with us, but us to be at <hi>peace</hi> &amp; amity with all <hi>diſſenting brethren</hi> &amp; they with <hi>us,</hi> &amp; will give us <hi>favour</hi> in the eyes of the <hi>Authority</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>In the</hi> Integrity <hi>of my heart have I done this,</hi> Gen. 20. 5.
<hi>Salem Philalathes,</hi> and a Church-member.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
